Computer graphics is the science of creating,
manipulating and using visual objects in a computer, CG for short.
You might think of CG as the art of creating drawings using software
like Blender or 3DMax or Photoshop.
But in computer science, computer graphics
is the art of developing software to create a graphical object.
There are three main categories of details in computer graphics.
"Modeling" is the field of how to express geometric objects inside a computer,
and it has to do with mathematical expressions and data structure.
"Rendering" is about how the modeled objects are drawn on the screen,
Photorealistic rendering is attempting to replicate the real world,
non-photorealistic rendering,
which mimics other artistic practices.
Animations are possible by changing the time
so that each frame, each scene, can be rendered sequentially.
The area where we study how to calculate the changes in trajectory
or shape of an object over time is called "animation."
A related field to CG is "image/video processing",
which involves manipulating images or videos.
In particular, the processing of photos or videos
taken by cameras for special purposes is
called "computational photography".
"Human-computer interaction",
often shortened to "HCI",
is the study of the devices and interaction methods
involved in human use of computing devices.
"Visualization" is often divided into two fields:
scientific visualization and
information visualization,
which were considered early applications of CG.
"Extended reality," which includes "virtual reality"
and "augmented reality,"
is one of the most exciting applications of CG in recent years.
"3D printing" is the process of taking a computer modeled object
and producing it with real-world materials,
and that's one of the fastest advances in technology in recent years.
The most famous application of CG is filmmaking.
These days, it's very common to make a movie with a combination of live-action
photography and CG, which allows you to make scenes that don't exist
in reality for relatively little money.
But in order to create sophisticated graphics results
that are indistinguishable from reality,
it may require computing that takes minutes, hours, or even days per frame.
Another application is games.
Rendering your scenes in real time is essential, especially in a game.
Real-time graphics generally requires a rendering speed of at least 30 frames per second,
so it's important to balance the quality of your rendering
with the speed of your render calculations.
These days, with game engines like Unity and Unreal,
it's a lot easier to build games,
and one of the most important techniques that we use in game engines is CG.
Computer graphics technology has been used in a wide
variety of fields beyond entertainment
including the design of construction and machinery, visualization,
training and education (ex. flight simulators),
and media arts.
In order for us to draw on our computer screens,
we need to take input from our input devices first.
We can input that from a keyboard, from a tablet, from a mouse, et cetera.
The input is first stored in the CPU memory and then processed in a variety of ways.
This data then moves to the GPU memory
inside the GPU (Graphics Processing Unit).
In particular, the memory that's storing the pixel values that are
currently being drawn on the screen is called a frame buffer.
And the frame buffer is going to continue to be drawn on the screen at a very high rate of speed.
So we're going to keep changing the content in this frame buffer
so that we can see moving picture (animation)
Raster is a set of pixels.
Pixel is short for picture element.
One pixel has a color that represents a location that's going to take a coordinate on the screen.
The frame buffer that's storing the raster that's currently displayed
is actually a set of different buffers.
A frame buffer consists of a color buffer
that stores the color values of pixel,
a depth buffer that stores the depth values, and so on.
Scan conversion, also known as rasterization, is the process of converting polygons
like triangles into pixel data.
In order to draw a triangle on the screen like you drew it,
you have to decide which PIXELs to turn on and off.
The Scan conversion is one of those things that the GPU does exclusively for CG.
GPUs have graphical memory, like frame buffers,
and they implement some special algorithms in H/W
to make it run faster.
The GPU was originally developed for computer graphics,
but more recently, it's been widely used for calculated machine learning, electronic currency mining, and so on.
Before the flat-pannel display, which we'll talk about later,
the most common output that was used was CRT (Cathode-Ray-Tube).
The CRT was a raster display
that displayed the entire contents of the frame buffer.
The path of electrons fired from the CRT's electromagnetic gun
is bent by magnetic force against the XY deflectors
to reach the desired coordinates on the screen.
On the CRT screen, there are colored florescent materials called phosphors
that glow when electrons hit them.
The speed at which a CRT is drawn is called a refresh rate.
In the U.S., it's usually re-drawing at 60 times a second,
or 60 Herz, as we call it.
In Europe, 50 hertz is the number that's commonly used.
When you do a refresh, once you draw an odd number of rows,
the next time you draw an even number of rows, it's called interacing.
If you use interacing,
the 60 hertz refresh is actually a 30 hertz refresh.
The most popular display these days
is Flat-panel display.
They contain light emitting elements between two 2D grids,
one vertical and one horizontal,
and use the two grids to specify where light is visible.
Depending on the technology that makes the light emitting elements,
flat-panel displays are categorized as LCD, LED, OLED, etc.
There's a lot of different types of input devices for computer graphics.
The mouse is something we use a lot, and we use it a lot in graphics.
You have a trackball that has a free 360-degree rotation
It's often used to roll a ball with your palm and type in rotation or something like that.
The tablet is often used to draw more intricately with a pen.
We're seeing a lot of high-end tablets that are drawn directly on the screen with touch pens.
Joysticks are very common for things like game play.
Spaceball is kind of like a trackball, but you're not actually rolling the ball,
you're holding the fixed ball and touching it.
OpenGL's home page is opengl.org.
OpenGL provides a lot of functionality for graphics and for images.
OpenGL is not an API, it's not an Application Programming Interface,
But it's a specification of an API.
In other words, OpenGL is a standard that describes
what functions and variables exist.
This means that OpenGL can be implemented in
different programming languages including C++, Java, Python, and JavaScript.
GLFW is a library that comes with OpenGL that makes the window that you want to draw on
and then input and output from those devices.
GLEW is a library that looks for openGL functions
implemented by the manufacturer of graphic card to tie into our openGL applications.
We're going to be using a combination of GLFW and GLEW with OpenGL in this course.
So we're going to take a look at our first application.
00_HelloWindow is a simple program that displays a single window.
You can resize the window with the mouse just like any other window.
There are two ways to exit the program:
pressing the ESC key or pressing the Exit button.
So the first part of the program is to include two header files,
glew.h and glfw3.h. Below that is
the prototype of the two functions that are going to be defined later.
So the framebuffer_size_callback is a callback function that calls
when the window is resized.
processInput is a function that will check whether input has come in
during the execution of rendering loop.
The SCR_WIDTH and the SCR_HEIGHT are the global variable that represents the size of the Windows
that's going to be created.
We're going to create a window of size 800 x 600.
So at the beginning of the main function,
we initialize GLFW, and set an OpenGL version to 3.3.
And this is where it's going to create the window.
And we're setting the current context to the window that we just created.
So all of the next commands are going to work against this window.
And you'll see that
framebuffer_size_callback is registered as the FramebufferSizeCallback function.
And then the rest of this is showing the initialize of the glew.
This is the part of the main loop that actually draws on Windows
and processes it by input.
A lot of times that type of application will loop until the end event comes in, and within that loop,
it's going to check the input, the event,
and then it's going to draw whatever the update is.
A lot of times you'll see these loops in game programs.
We call them event loops or main loops.
So in our case we're going to check that
the quit event has come in through the glfwWindowShouldClose function,
and it's going to exit the loop if the end button or ESC key occurs.
And inside the loop the first thing it does is it takes a look at what input came in.
Typically, it's going to handle a mouse input or keyboard input or something like that.
And what glClearColor does is
it specifies the Windows background color.
They're in RGBA format, for example,  (0.2 or .3 or .3 or 1.0)
Here, Alpha 1.0  represents an completely opaque color.
glClear() is the function is to clear a specific buffer,
GL_COLOR_BUFFER_BIT is the buffer where everything that we're drawing
So we're saying color buffer within the frame buffer,
and with glClear() command, it's going to clear the window in the designated background color.
Our 00_HelloWindow program only shows the background,
so after you clear, you don't have to draw anything else.
When you're done drawing,
you give the command to the glfwSapBuffers to swap the buffer.
So it's the exchange between the front and the back buffer,
which we'll talk about in a little bit more detail in the later slides.
glfwPollEvents() is called at the end of the loop body
that monitors for the next input that's going to be processed.
So the termination event comes in, takes you out of your main loop,
and that's when you wrap up and you're done with your program.
glfwTerminate()  kills the drawing window.
we have two more functions except the main function.
So first of all, the processInput function is
checking what input event happened.
So in this example, We're going to check if the ESC key has come in,
and then the program is going to set WindowsShouldClose
to true to get it out of the main loop.
So the second one, the function is framebuffer_size_callback,
and you'll remember that this function was registered as a callback function.
This callback function is going to run as soon as the window size changes.
The width and height that comes in to the parameter are the sizes that were changed
the changed sizes are from GLFW.
So we're going to change the viewport size
to fit the new window size using the GLViewport function.
And then we're going to save the changed size of the window to
SCR_WIDTH and SCR_HEIGHT as global variables.
Generally, computers have two display buffers,
a front and a back buffer.
The display screen is always showing what's contained in the front buffer.
Meanwhile, the application is drawing something to the back buffer, not to the front.
So with one frame of animation displayed on the screen,
the application is going to draw the next frame of the back buffer.
and then we're going to replace the front with the back buffer.
In other words, we're going to replace the pointer of the front buffer
with a pointer that's pointing to a back buffer.
That can be helpful to prevent the flickering
that you get when you're drawing a new frame.
If we only use one single buffer, we'll get a blink.
You can see in the video the blink with the single buffering.
Viewport is the (part of ) area that's actually being drawn on the window.
Inside that already defined drawing window,
you define a left- to lower corner of the area
that you're actually going to draw, the width of that area, the height of that area.
If you call glViewPort(0, 0, width, height)
that's going to make the viewport to be the entire window.
That's also the default viewport.
Like the second example, we can only draw in the first quadrant of the window.
That way, we can actually draw multiple views on the same window at the same time.