In this notebook we're going to talk about the setup for coding
OpenGL in PC Windows.
First of all, update
your PC drivers with your latest stuff.
It's not necessarily required,
but it's best to do it for the best possible outcome.
We're going to go to the Visual Studio page
and download the community version of the Visual Studio 2022.
Set "Desktop development with C++" as a workload.
Before you create a project in Visual Studio,
you better open "tools > projects and solutions > locations,"
and start setting up new project locations.
In this example, we're going to create a new project under a new folder,
so we set a new location for the project.
We're going to download all the external libraries.
At first, we download GLEW, GLFW, and the glm files.
Then uncompress glew-xxx.zip with the option of "uncompress here."
And rename this folder glew-xxx-win32 to GLEW.
Then, create a folder called "External Libs" at the same level as "projects" folder.
And, put the GLEW folder inside of External Libs.
The current folder structure is shown in the figure.
Under the projects folder our projects go into each of different sub folders.
Then, uncompress glfw-xxx.zip as the option: "uncompress here".
Then rename the GLFW-xx.WIN64 folder to GLFW.
And put the GLFW folder under External Libs.
After that, you can see the following folder hierarchy.
Uncompress GLM-xxx.zip with the option of "here."
Rename the glm folder to GLM.
Under GLM,  delete all except the glm folder.
Move the GLM folder and put it under the External Libs folder.
After installing GLM, the folder structure should look like this.
Start to edit the file: External Libs > GLM > glm > glm.hpp
and you add a line with a picture.
If you don't do that, you should add this line to every source file
before you include the glm.hpp,
and we don't want to do that, so do it now.
Now downloaded the example source files from LearnUs,
then, copy the "utils" folder to the same level as External Libs and projects.
So now the folder structure should be like this.
Now, let's  create a new project in Visual Studio.
Select Console App, C++, and then click "Next".
Select and fill the Project name, Location name, and Solution name,
and click the Create button.
In our example, Project and Solution names
are set to "00_HelloWindow".
Location is defined as the projects folder that we created earlier.
Among the source codes, find "hello_window.cpp" in 00_HelloWindow folder,
and copy the file into the source code folder in the project that we just created.
the source code folder is  00_HelloWindow / 00_HelloWindow.
If you have a shader files (.vs, .fs) and any texture image files,
you better copy them into the same source folder.
We'll see that in a later source project.
We'll add the hello_window.cpp that we just copied into our project.
In the solution explorer you'll find a menu by clicking the right mouse button click.
and select "source file" and click on "add existing files",
then you'll be able to add hello_window.cpp into the project.
By right mouse button clicking on your project name in the Solution
Select "Property" at the bottom of the pop-up menu.
Select C/C+ > general > additional directory
and then you can add four include directories.
Here $(SolutionDir) represents
the folder of the current project,
which is common for all of other projects to represent each of the project folders.
On a property > linker > general > additional library directory,
Add two directories.
And add the follwing three libraries at linker > input > additional dependencies,
opengl32.lib, glew32.lib, glfw3.lib
Copy the glew32.dll in External Libs > GLEW > bin > Release > Win32
into the source folder of project.
Finally, pressing "Control F5" allows you to build the application and run it.