In this notebook I'm going to walk you through the process of building
and launching an OpenGL program using Xcode on the Mac.
Xcode is the IDE or Integrated Development Environment
provided by MacOS.
This is a setup course that was done as a test on Xcode version
15.2 in early February 2024.
If it's Xcode and not this version, then we do need to update it.
We do need to have all these external libraries,
and the easiest way to get them to install is with Homebrew.
Homebrew is downloadable from http://brew.sh/installable. So I can do a Homebrew install,
and then I can do a BREW command,
so I can install GLFW, GLEW, GLM.
After I've done all the installs,
if I go into the terminal app and I go into the CD command, /usr/local/Cellar folder,
you'll see that I've got GLEW, GLFW, GLM in the install.
If you go to /usr/local/include, you'll see that the GL, the GLFW
and the GLM folders are all linked to the appropriate folders that have been installed previously.
So glew.h is under /usr/local/include/GL.
So we prepare a working folder for projects.
So in this example, I've created a folder called MAC.
So I'm going to open the source.zip that I downloaded from Runus,
and I'm going to do a working folder or laro copy of the utils folder.
So what we're going to do is we're going to create a project for Xcode to use OpenGL.
So I'm going to do Project template MOS > "Command Line Tool"
and I'm going to click next.
I'm going to type in the name of Project, and language is going to do C++.
And for this, I'm going to do a project name of 00
underscore, Working folder (ex.
MAC) and I'm going to click the create button.
Under the Working Folder there's a project folder called 00_HellowWindow.
I'm going to hit the "Frameworks and Libraries" button under the general tab,
and I'm going to search opengl, select the opengl framework, add it.
"Frameworks and Libraries" below,
+ button, "Add Other", "Add Files" select.
Command – Shift – G and pull up the "go to the folder" dialogue.
So we're going to type in the folder that we want to go to,
which is /usr/local/Cellar, and we're going to hit enter.
under /usr/local/Cellar, you go to the glew folder,
you go to the lib folder under the install glew packages,
and you select a dylib file.
The first thing to note is that we're going to need to select an actual dylib file, not just the virtual file ( link)
We'll know whether it's a virtual file or an actual file when we look at the file icon.
Similarly we're going to add a dylib file for GLFW.
So we've got three libraries of openGL framework,
libGLEW and libglfw in this programming course.
So we're going to add in the header search paths /usr/local/include
and we're going to add in .utils.
When we create a project, we don't need the default main.cpp, so we delete that.
I'm going to copy the 00_HellowWindow project
hello_window.cpp from the distributed source to the 00_HelloWindow/00_HelloWindow folder,
click right on the 00_HelloWindow project and select from the pop-up menu
"Add Files to 00_HelloWindow."
And I'm going to add a copy of hello_window.cpp to my project
by clicking the add button.
I'm going to select hello_window.cpp on the navigation area on the left
and I'm going to see the source code.
I'm going to hit the play button and I'm going to run the program.
So I'm going to run it and it's going to pop up a window
and it's going to pop up a grey-green background.
So I'm going to press ESC key on the keyboard
or I'm going to click the end red button
and that's going to end the program.
The Derived Data folder is the folder for storing the build up run files.
It's also the folder that we need to be aware of
to be able to store our shader files, our texture files, et cetera,
to be able to run our applications.
And to find out where the current Derived Data folder is,
I'm going to go to Xcode > Settings menu.
If I go to the "Locations" tab,
it's going to take me to the current default "Derived Data" folder.
you're usually going to see a default
location for "s/user/user name/library/Developer/Xcode/Derivedata."
Username is your current user ID.
I'm going to turn the Derived Data folder
into a more accessible folder,
select the "Custom" option, and then specify the folder that I've chosen.
So under MAC, project directory, I'm going to create a folder called Derived Data,
and I'm going to specify that.
So I'm going to do build,
and you're going to see that
the executable, 00_HelloWindow, has come up under MAC/DerivedData/00_HelloWindow... /Build/Products/Debug.
So we can put any of the shader files or texture files
that we want into a directory such as the executable files.
21_Texture1 is our source that contains all of our texture files,
our mage files, our fragment
shader files, all of our fragment shader files.
So you can create a project in Xcode and run it in order to get it running.
The texture file, container.bmp, and the two shader files,
global.fs and global.vs, under the Derivedata folder
that you've chosen, 21_Texture1..../Builder/Products/Debug,
you need to copy that.
But that folder doesn't exist without the first play,
the build, so we're going to copy the build before we copy the first three files.
So these need to exist under the derived data directory.
So just to make it easier for Xcode to edit the shader files,
just like we added the CPP files,
you can add the FS files from the Derived Data folder into the 21_Texture1 folder.