In this notebook we're going to look at drawing a 2D Triangle.
VBO is memory in the GPU
where vertex data, i.e., attributes, is stored.
Vertex attributes include
vertex coordinates, vertex color,
texture coordinates, and normal vector.
We know what the vertex coordinates and color are.
And we'll learn more about the rest as we go along.
The vertex data inside the CPU is
batch-transferred to VBO as a chunk,
and that's a feature of the core profile
distinguished from the immediate mode.
What's interesting here is
there's no special format
predetermined for storing data on VBO.
That means that the developers are free to choose
the format that he/she want to store it in the VBO.
Which part of the 3D space, can OpenGL draw?
It can be drawn in the window
if the X, Y and Z coordinates are
all in the space between [-1, 1].
We call these coordinate systems
NDC or Normalized Device Coordinates.
Later, we'll talk about camera deployments and
various transformations,but for the time being,
assuming that we're only going to use a default camera,
we're only going to use vertices
having the coordinates contained in the NDC space.
So for the time being,
we're only going to use the things
between the -1 and 1, in x, y, and z coordinates.
Homogeneous coordinates represent
an N-dimensional position as (N+1) dimension Vector.
So the 3D position is represented with a 4D vector.
To convert a homogeneous 4D vector,  [x', y', z', w],
to 3D coordinates,
we divide the last x', y', z' by w.
So 4D homogeneous coordinates [x, y, z, 1] equals
3D coordinates [x, y, z].
Here w = 1.
For example, the 3D coordinates p = [1, 2, 3],
is converted into the 4D homogeneous p' = [1, 2, 3, 1].
by adding w = 1 at the end of the coordinates.
The 4D homogeneous coordinates, p = [2, 4, 6, 2],
is converted into the 3D coordinates p = [1, 2, 3],
by dividing 2, 4, 6, by w = 2.
And these two above examples mean that
the 4D homogeneous coordinates
[1, 2, 3, 1] is the same as [2, 4, 6, 2].
There are many reasons
for using 4D homogeneous coordinates.
However, the most intuitive reason
is to express all possible transformation operations,
such as translation, as 4 x 4 matrix operations.
We will learn about this later in the transformation part.
We're going to talk about basic openGL
drawing using Program 02_HelloTriangle.
So now it's time to look at a program that draws triangles.
I defined the coordinates of the three vertexes of the triangles
in a float array called vertices.
The Z coordinates are all uniform to zero
because we're going to draw a 2D triangle.
The rest of the X and Y coordinates are
all defined as coordinates within the NDC space.
We're going to draw a triangle, so
we've declared a variable VBO to store the ID of the VBO.
Then, we call glenBuffers () to generate one buffer,
and get an ID returned to VBO.
To copy the data into the GL_ARRAY_BUFFER,
we first bind the current VBO with glBindBuffer().
Finally, we copy the data from the vertices
into the VBO with glBufferData().
Here, size found by sizeof() is representing current size of vertices.
If you want to draw something,
at least a very simple shader must exist.
Shader is an independent program
that takes over the objects to be drawn
from the OpenGL program and gives commands to the GPU.
Here we introduce a very simple vertex shader.
At the top of the Vertex shader program
is a version of the OpenGL Shading Language (GLSL).
We are using version 3.3 here.
The syntax of GLSL is similar to the C language.
Our first vertex shader receives
only one vertex attribute from the OpenGL program,
that is, the vertex position coordinates.
Remember that the attributes stored
in the VBO previously were vertex coordinates.
aPos is the "in" variable defined in the vertex shader.
Its value flows from the OpenGL program
to the vertex shader.
layout (location = 0) is the location
where variable exists, i.e, the address value.
In this case, location is 0.
The type of aPos variable is vec3.
It stores x, y, z values ​​all at once in 3D vector.
Now it's the body part of the vertex shader program
that starts with void main ().
A predefined variable named gl_Position
is assigned a 4D homogeneous coordinates value
by adding a value of w = 1.0
to the input x, y, z value of aPos.
This gl_Position variable is a value that represents the position
that one vertex should actually have,
and is used in future operations within the GPU.
The source code for the simple vertex shader program
introduced earlier was created as one long string.
We create a vertex shader object with the glCreateShader().
We assign the source code to it with the glShaderSource()
We compile the vertex shader with the glCompileShader()
The following part is where we check
if there is an error while compiling the shader and handle it.
The Fragment shader is one of two shaders
that must exist for rendering,
along with the Vertex shader.
The Fragment shader is responsible for calculating the pixel color
that should ultimately be displayed on the screen.
Color is represented in RGBA format.
Each of the four components, Red, Green, Blue, and Alpha,
is represented by a value between 0 and 1.
Alpha is a value that represents transparency,
where 0 is completely transparent and 1 is completely opaque.
FragColor is the "out" variable, which passes
the color output of the final pixel to the display hardware.
Here we've assigned a single color
(1.0, 0.5, 0.2, 1.0) to the FragColor,
which is the orange color of the triangle we saw earlier
in the still image of the program running.
This figure illustrates the relationship between
the OpenGL application program, the vertex shader,
and the fragment shader.
Vertex attribute is passed from the application program
to the vertex shader, where the final coordinates of the vertex,
called gl_Position, are calculated
and passed to the graphics hardware.
On the other side, the color of a pixel is determined
in the Fragment shader and passed to the hardware.
In fact, there needs to be some information passed
from the application program or the vertex shader
to the fragment shader to determine the color,
but that doesn't happen in this program yet.
This part shows the source code
of the fragment shader as a string
in an OpenGL application and compiles it.
The basic content is the same as compiling the vertex shader,
so Let us skip it.
Now it is time to create a shader program object
with the compiled vertex and fragment shaders
and link them together.
The shader program object is created with glCreateProgram().
The vertex and fragment shader objects are then attached
to the created shader program object,
which is done by the glAttachShader() function.
After attaching, the shader program object is then linked
using the glLinkProgram() function.
Checking and handling linking errors is similar
to the compile process.
The vertex and fragment shader objects
can be deleted because they are no longer needed
after the shader program object is created.
Using a shader program in an
OpenGL application program is simple.
All we need to do is specify a shader program object
to use with the glUseProgram() function. From then on,
the shader program will be responsible for all drawing.
You can also create multiple shaders
and select different shaders to use
for rendering depending on the situation.
Now let's take a look at the process of passing
the vertex attributes contained in the VBO to the vertex shader.
The VBO we created is in the format shown in this image.
The 3D coordinates of the three vertices
are put into the buffer one after the other,
The coordinates for each dimension are float type,
so they take up 32 bits, or 4 bytes.
Therefore, we need 3 x 3 x 4 = 36 bytes
for the three vertices.
Also, there are no spaces, or any other kind of data,
between the coordinates of the vertices.
This means that the coordinates of one vertex are
immediately followed by the coordinates of the next vertex.
Overall, all data starts at the beginning of the buffer,
which is why the offset value is given as 0.
Stride is the number of bytes occupied
by each vertex's attribute data.
Here, it is 3 x 4 = 12, as we calculated above.
We need to tell the vertex shader the structure of the VBO
created by your OpenGL application
so that the vertex shader can read
the vertex attribute data correctly.
The function that does this is glVertexAttribPointer().
In this example, location refers to the location of the variable
in the vertex shader, which has a value of 0.
The number of Components is 3 because it is xyz.
The type is GL_FLOAT.
The normalized parameter is true  if the attribute values are
normalized between the range [0, 1],
In this case, we don't do any special calculations
on the vertex coordinates values, so we leave it GL_FALSE.
Stride is the number of bytes occupied by the attributes in
one vertex portion, so we set it to 3 * sizeof(float).
offset is 0 because the first data is
starting from the beginning of the buffer.
glEnableVertexAttribArray() enables the variable location = 0
in the vertex shader
based on the information provided by glVertexAttribPointer().
In this way, the glVertexAttribPointer and
glEnableVertexAttribArray functions are
paired and used together.
VAO stands for Vertex Array Object,
which is an object that contains
multiple VBOs at once.
When an object is often represented
by a combination of multiple VBOs,
it can be complicated to bind and render them individually.
VAOs simplify this process.
In the illustration, the first object stores
its position attribute in VBO1 and its color attribute in VBO2.
We can bind these two VBOs into a single VAO1,
and by binding only VAO1,
we can easily specify the render state.
On the other hand, the second object at the bottom
has both the position and color attributes
stored in a single VBO3.
In this case, we can still have VAO2 contain the VBO3.
We use the glGenVertexArray() to generate a VAO.
Then, we creates the VBOs that will belong to the VAO.
And call glBindVertexArray to bind the VAO.
After that, perform normal VBO operations.
We bind the VBO, copy the data,
and pass the attributes to the vertex shader.
Any VBOs that are created while one VAO is bound
in this way will belong to the currently bound VAO.
Now that the VBO belongs to a VAO, it's easy to specify
what to draw when the appropriate VAO is selected.
In the Rendering loop, we specify the VAO and shader
to draw and use glDrawArrays() to render the primitive.
The parameter to glDrawArrays specifies the primitive,
which in this case is GL_TRIANGLES.
The following parameters specify
the starting index of the VAO and the number of vertices.
There are several primitives that
OpenGL can draw, such as GL_TRIANGLES.
The numbering of the vertices in the figure indicates
the order of the vertices stored in the VBO.
GL_POINTS draws points one by one,
GL_LINES draws line segments
connecting two consecutive vertices.
GL_LINE_LOOP will render a loop
connecting the last vertex to the first vertex.
GL_LINE_STRIP draws a line connecting
a series of given vertices one after the other.
GL_TRIANGLES draws triangles
with the given vertices in groups of three.
GL_TRIANGLE_STRIP defines a triangle
with the first three given vertices
and creates a new triangle
for each additional given vertex.
GL_TRIANGLE_FAN is similar to GL_TRIANGLE_STRIP,
except that it creates triangles
centered on
the first given vertex.
There are no other primitives defined for
rectangles or other polygons.
This figure shows the different stages of the graphics pipeline.
The vertex data passed to the GPU goes through
vertex shader, shape assembly, geometry shader,
rasterization, fragment shader, and tests and blending
to become visible on the screen.
The parts of the steps that are colored blue
are shaders which are programmable.
The gray steps are features provided by the GPU
, often built into the hardware,
that allow for very fast processing.
In this course, we will only be studying
vertex shader and fragment shader.