Let's start with the Indexed Triangle lesson.
In this program, we're going to draw
a single rectangle using two triangles,
and unlike the previous example, we're using INDEX
to specify the vertex data.
By pressing the 'r' key, we can toggle between
painting the inside of the triangle
or showing only the edges.
Consider the case of drawing a rectangle with two triangles.
Since each triangle requires three vertices,
do we need data for all six vertices?
When we place these six vertex coordinates in the vertices array,
we see that the bottom right and top left
are common to both triangles.
So we actually only need four vertices.
In this case, there is a way to use indexes.
This means that we don't put duplicate data in the vertex data,
but store the connection (topology) information
for primitives like triangles separately in an index array.
In this example, we only use the four vertex coordinates
and use the vertex indices
to define the two triangles.
While the advantages of using indexes are not apparent
in this example, the reduction in data volume can be significant
when creating complex models with tens of thousands of triangles.
Index is called Element in OpenGL.
Like VBOs, indexes can be buffered.
This is called an Element Buffer Object (EBO).
To create an EBO and get its id, use the glGenBuffers() function
just as we would for a VBO.
When binding the EBO and copying data to it,
use GL_ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER as the target.
In the case of VBO, GL_ARRAY_BUFFER as a target.
The process of bind and copy is very similar to what VBO does.
The one thing to note is that even after you've created an EBO,
you better not to unbind it.
Another thing to note is that VAO can contain both VBOs and EBOs.
Let's take a look at the drawing operations inside the man loop.
The processInput() function is gone
that was there before glClear().
So how do we check if the ESC and r keys are pressed?
We moved that functionality to the keyboard callback function.
glPolygonMode() allows you to specify whether
painting the inside of the polygon
or just draw edges.
It's sort of a command that changes the drawing state.
fillTriangle is a global variable that will alternate between true/false
each time the "r" key is pressed in the keyboard callback.
If true, it will paint the inside,
and if false, it will draw with GL_LINE, or edges.
glDrawElements() is a function
that draws objects by index.
GL_TRIANGLES is the primitive target and
there are six indices, two triangles,
and the last parameter, 0, is the offset from the start.
To use the keyboard callback,
we register the callback function in advance
using the glfwSetKeyCallback() function.
In this example, we registered a function called
key_callback() as a callback function.
Among the parameters of the Keyboard callback function,
'key' indicates which key,
and 'action' indicates whether the key is pressed (GLFW_PRESS)
or released (GLFW_RELEASE).
Each action can have different event handling.
In this case, the window is closed when the ESC key is pressed,
and the value of a global variable called fillTriangle to toggle
between true and false when the 'r' key is pressed.
In the following sections, we will look at the programs
for three example programs that are variations of HelloTriangle.
First, in 04_HelloTriangleExample1,
we draw two triangles, using one VAO and one VBO.
This program is almost identical
to the original 02_HelloTriangle program.
The only difference is that the vertices data now contains
the position coordinates of six vertices instead of three.
The rest of the process for creating the VAO and VBO are
all the same as when drawing just one triangle.
And when we call glDrawArrays in the main loop,
we use 6 vertices as the target of GL_TRIANGLES,
so we set the last parameter to 6.
One vertex coordinate is shared by both triangles,
but we didn't use index in this example.
The second example uses two different VAOs and VBOs
to draw two triangles.
To give the two VBOs different data,
we prepared two arrays with three vertex data each.
Both VAOs and VBOs were generated using two arrays of id.
And bind, buffering, and passing were done separately.
Note that if we bind VAOs[0] first,
all subsequent VBOs will belong to VAOs[0],
and if we bind VAOs[1],
all subsequent VBOs will belong to VAOs[1].
When we used glVertexAttribPointer
to pass the buffer data into the shader,
we gave the stride a value of 12 for the top and 0 for the bottom,
which all mean the same thing.
This means that if the data is
tightly packed with no other space between them,
writing a 0 will mean the same thing as writing a 12.
Finally, when we draw the two triangles,
we bind different VAOs to them
and call the DrawArrays command to use different data.
The third example draws two triangles, orange and yellow.
To use different colors,
this example uses two different fragment shaders.
The fragmentShader1Source string
is the source of the fragment shader that uses the orange color.
fragmentShader2Source is
the source of the fragment shader that uses the yellow color.
Since one shader program is
a pair of vertex shader and fragment shader,
we need two shader programs
to use different fragment shaders.
Unlike before,
we create another shader object
for the yellow fragment shader.
By combining the vertex shader and orange fragment shader,
the first shader program has been completed.
And the other shader program
uses the same vertex shader,
but different fragment shader.
VAO and VBO have created two of each just like we did in Example 2.
and used separately on the two triangles.
There's no change there.
When we're rendering on the main loop,
when we draw the first triangle,
we use the shaderProgramOrange, and then bind VAOs[0],
and then we draw it.
For the second triangle, we use shaderProgramYellow,
bind VAOs[1], and then draw it.