We will study at this time about vectors and geometry
in mathematical graphics theory.
Many things are very basic,
and these are things that you already knew.
Even so, let's study together in the sense of reviewing.
The right-handed coordinate system
is the coordinate system we typically use in math class.
The OpenGL APIs we'll be using in this course
also use the right-handed coordinate system.
In CG, the y-axis is typically oriented overhead.
The +z axis is the direction out from the screen.
Make the thumb, index, and middle fingers of your right hand,
perpendicular to each other, The fingers point in the direction of
the x, y, and z axes of the r-h coord. system, in that order.
In the left-handed coord. system,
z-axis is pointing to the inside of the screen.
In CG, we use this left-handed coordinate system
in the camera coordinate system,
which we'll learn about in the viewing transformation.
We will study this later.
The World coordinate system is the only coordinate system
that exists within the CG scene we will be drawing.
All objects are placed in this world coordinate system
to be displayed in a scene.
The Local coordinate system is the coordinate system
that is mainly used when modeling (designing) each part or object.
Even when modeling tilted objects like this, they are usually
initially modeled straight and centered on the origin.
The local coordinate system plays an important role,
especially when animating multi-linked bodies connected by joints,
such as the human body.
In the figure, the world coords. of red dot is (3, 1).
But after rotating the local system w.r.t. origin,
followed by some translation, the world coords. would be (4, 5).
Later, we'll study more about
converting from local to world coords.
Vector has orientation and size (magnitude)
For example, the vector from point P1 to P2 can be
computed by P2 - P1.
Vectors have direction and size, but no fixed positions.
So these three vectors in the picture are all the same vector.
Whereas scalas are made up of just one component
with no direction, but just magnitude (size).
For example, 3 and 235.5 are scalars.
So let's say you have two vectors V and W.
The sum V+W and difference V-W are like this.
The sum of two vectors represents a new vector,
and you can draw it in these two ways.
If you match the tails of
a and b at the same point
a - b is a vector from the  head of b to the head of a.
You can also draw a - b like this, because a - b is the same as a + (-b)
Two vectors a+(-b) and a-b are in different positions,
but they have the same direction and magnitude,
so they're exactly the same vectors.
The magnitude (size) of the vector is sometimes called length, size,
and norm, the lengths from the tail to the head,
is the square root of the sum of the square of each component.
Normalization means make the size of the vector one,
keeping the direction of the vector.
By dividing each component of the vector by its magnitude
we can normalize the vector.
Especifically, we call the vector of magnitude 1 "unit vector".
The dot product V.W of two vectors V and W
is defined like this.
It is the sum of the multiples of each component of two vectors.
Here, theta is the angle between two vectors.
So, if we know the value of dot product,
we can get theta using the arc cosine.
The result of dot product is a scalar value.
So dot product is sometimes called scalar product,
or inner product.
Particularly the dot product v.v is
the square of the magnitude of the vector, ||v||^2.
Let's consider how to find the vector w,
which is the projection of v onto u.
First of all, by the definition of cosine, the size of w is
the multiplication of the size of v and cosine theta.
Also, by the definition of the dot product of u and v,
the size of w is (u.v) divided by the size of u.
So if u is an unit vector,
then w is going to be u.v.
The direction of w is the same as u, and we've decided the size of w,
w can be represented like this.
Now let's look at the relationship between
the size of angle theta and dot product.
If dot product is positive,
cosine theta is positive, too.
That means theta is somewhere in between 0 and 90 degree.
So theta is an acute angle.
When dot product is a negative,
cosine theta is negative, too.
So theta is an obtuse angle larger than 90 degree.
If dot product is exactly zero,
then two vectors are vertical, that is, theta is 90 degrees.
This relationship comes in
very handy for a lot of graphics operations.
Assume we have a polygon here.
How do we get the normal vector of the polygon?
Normal vector N is the cross product of two vectors
V1 and V2 on top of that polygon.
Bear in mind, V1, V2 and N form a
right-handed coordinate system.
If we try V2 cross V1 rather than V1 cross V2,
we can get the normal vector having opposite direction of N.
So how do you get the cross product for V1 and V2?
The cross product is computed using determinant.
We compute 3x3 determinants by using 2x2 determinants.
Here, i, j, and k are the unit vector in the x, y and z axes directions.
The result of the cross product is vector, not scalar.
So cross product is sometimes called vector product,
or outer product.
We can get the size of the cross product vector with this formula:
When A x B = C,  the size of C = (size of A) x (sizeof B) x sin (theta).
Here, theta is the angle between vector A and B.
So if A and B are unit vector, the size of C is the same as sin(theta).
Line means an infinite straight line.
We don't have a start point and an end point of a line.
A line segment is defined with a start and an end point,
and has a finite length.
When only a start point, no end point, it is specifically called a ray.
The general implicit form of a 2D line is
f (x, y) = ax + by + c = 0.
The two points form when two points are given are like this:
Given two points p1 and p2,
the two points parametric form of the line
C (t) = (x (t), y (t)).
Here, t is a parameter and since it is an infinite line,
the range of t is also from minus infinity to infinity.
x(t) is x1 + (x2 - x1)t.
Writing this out with respect to x1 and x2 is x1 (1-t) + x2 t.
This is the x component of the parametric line C(t).
Similarly, y (t) is an expression of y component.
That is, C (t) can be seen as a vector form
with x(t) and y(t) together.
When t is zero, C(0) becomes (x1, y1), or p1.
When t is 1, C(1) becomes (x2, y2), or p2.
Another form of parametric form is point and vector form.
C (t) = p1 + vt, where p1 is a point on the line
and v is the direction vector of the line.
The two points form can be rearranged in terms of t.
Then, it is the same as the points and vector form.
Therefore, even if we use different methods,
they represent the same line.
We are given an implicit 2D line f.
Computing the partial derivative of f with respect to x
and the partial derivative with respect to y
gives the vector (a, b).
This vector is the normal vector N perpendicular to the line.
The tangent vector T = (-b, a),
which is the vector perpendicular to the normal vector,
is the same as the directional vector of the line.
We get it by taking the y component of N, b, as x component in T,
with attaching minus,
and sending a to the y component of T.
We can see the normal and tangent vectors are perpendicular
by the fact that the dot product N and T is zero.
Now consider the line in parametric form C(t).
The tangent vector T(t) can be found
by differentiating x(t) and y(t) with respect to t, respectively.
The normal vector N(t) is perpendicular to T(t),
so it can be found just as easily as in the previous case.
For line segments where the start and end points are defined,
the implicit form is not easy to use.
The two points parametric form is the most appropriate.
The range of the parameter t in C(t) = (x(t), y(t)) is
clearly defined to be between 0 and 1.
We can represent x(t) and y(t) as something like an infinite line.
By substituting 0 and 1 for t, we can see that
the starting point C(0) and the ending point C(1) are obtained.
Let's look at an example.
Given two points p1 and p2,
we want to find the implicit line that passes through them.
We can easily find the implicit line f(x,y) = 0
by using two point form formula.
The parametric line C(t) is also easy
to find from the two points.
We also found the tangent and normal vector from C(t).
However, if we try to find the normal from the implicit form f(x,y),
we get (a, b) = (2, -1),
which is the opposite direction from the parametric form.
This is an orientation problem in geometry.
This is because we cannot determine
the direction the normal of this line is
based on the two given points alone.
To overcome this problem, we need to include other information,
which we will learn more about later.
Consider a circle with center at (a, b) and radius r.
We have
f(x, y) = (x - a)^2 + (y - b)^2 - r^2 = 0,
in implicit form.
In parametric form, we have
c(theta) = (x(theta), y(theta))
= (a + r cos(theta), b + r sin(theta)).
Consider the equation of an ellipse
whose center is at (h, k) and whose two axes are of lengths a, b.
The implicit form looks like this.
The parametric form looks like this.
Now consider the intersection of a circle and a line.
Circle is given in implicit form.
Line is given in parametric form.
Substitute x(t) and y(t) into x, y in the implicit equation for circle.
This equation is a quadratic equation with respect to t.
Let's solve this quadratic equation.
If this equation has two roots,
then line and circle intersect at two points.
By substituting the two t's into C(t),
we can get the two points of intersection.
If the equation has only one root,
then line is tangent to circle at one point.
If the equation hasno roots,
then there is no intersection of line and circle.
In general, in an operation to find the
intersection of two objects A and B,
we can easily find the intersection
by making one implicit
and the other parametric.
Let's look at an example of finding the
intersection of a circle and a line segment.
First, the line segment is given by the two endpoints p1 and p2.
The equation of the parametric line through the two points is
L(t) = (x(t), y(t)),
which is given by x(t) = at + b, y(t) = ct + d.
Here, the range of t is limited to between 0 and 1.
This is because a line segment is only valid between two endpoints.
The equation of the circle is defined
in implicit form as (x-e)^2 + (y-f)^2 = r^2 ,
where (e,f) are the center and r is the radius of the circle.
Now we substitute x(t) and y(t) from the equation of the line
into x and y, respectively, of the equation of the circle.
This gives us the quadratic equation
At^2 + Bt + C = 0 with respect to t.
To find the roots of the quadratic equation,
consider the discriminant D = B^2 - 4AC.
For D > 0, there are two roots t.
When D = 0, there is one t.
When D < 0, there is no real root.
However, for the two cases where a real root exists,
we still need to verify the root t is between 0 and 1.
In this case, the line segment spans the circle, D > 0, has two roots,
and both t's are between 0 and 1.
This is when D > 0 and two t's are computed,
but one root is invalid because the line segment is short,
meaning that one t is not between 0 and 1.
This is also the case when D > 0
and two t's are found, but neither is between 0 and 1.
We can now substitute only valid t into the line equation L(t)
to get a valid intersection.
This time, we'll look at lines in 3D.
First, we're given two points p1 and p2 in three dimensions.
The parametric line C(t) is represented
by the components x(t), y(t), and z(t).
The representation of x(t), y(t), and z(t) is the same as for a 2D line,
and can be found as follows.
Substituting 0 and 1 fort, respectively,
we see that we get the two points C(0) and C(1).
That's the point-vector form of 3D line.
Like 2D, C (t) can be represented as p1 + vt
using a point p1 on the line and a direction vector v.
When representing a 3D line in an implicit form,
it is not possible to use only one equation.
It should be represented by two equations as shown here.
The former is about the equation for x and y, the latter about y and z.
Now let's look at plane and plane patch.
It's important to distinguish between plane and plane patch.
A plane is infinite and has no explicit scope.
A plane patch is a finite piece of a plane.
A plane patch is explicitly given its scope.
f(x,y) = Ax + By + Cz + D = 0,
which is the plane equation in implicit form.
Here, the vector n = (A, B, C) is the normal vector in the plane.
Let's derive the plane equation.
First, we are given the normal vector n = (A, B, C).
We are also given a point p = (x1, y1, z1) on the plane.
In this case, the plane is the set of all points r = (x, y, z)
such that the vectors n and (r - p) are perpendicular.
Therefore, the dot product of n and (r - p) is zero.
Solving and rewriting this expression, we have Ax + By + Cz + D = 0.
Here, D = - (A, B, C).(x1, y1, z1) = -n.p.
Suppose we are given a point P1
and a plane Ax + By + Cz + D = 0 in three dimensions.
Determine whether P1 is on the plane,
outside the plane,
or inside the plane.
Substitute P1's coordinates (x1, y1, z1) into the plane equation
to calculate the value of Ax1 + By1 + Cz1 + D.
If that value is zero, then P1 is on the plane.
If the value is negative, P1 is inside the plane.
If the value is positive, P1 is outside the plane.
Outside is the direction the plane normal vector is pointing.
How can we find the plane
that contains all three points p1, p2, and p3?
First, we can find the two vectors (p2 - p1) , (p3 - p1) starting at p1.
Since the normal vector must be perpendicular to both vectors,
we can find it as the cross product of the two vectors.
We are remembering that the two vectors (p2 - p1), (p3 - p1),
and the normal vector
represent a right-handed coordinate system
with the x, y, and z directions in turn.
Since there is a point above the normal vector and the plane,
the implicit equation for the plane
can be found as in the slide just a moment ago.
This time, let's look at the parametric form of a plane.
The plane r can be represented as p + sv + tw.
where s and t are parameters that are infinite intervals.
P is an arbitrary point on the plane.
V and W are vectors starting at P having different directions.
V and W are not necessarily perpendicular,
but they must not be parallel to each other.
In other words, v and w must be two linearly independent vectors.
The implicit form f(x,y,z) of a sphere
with center at (xc, yc, zc) and radius R is
(x-xc)^2 + (y-yc)^2 + (z-zc)^2 - R^2 = 0.
Let's find the intersection of this sphere with line C(t).
The sphere is implicit and the line is parametric.
This is a good way to find the intersection,
as mentioned earlier.
We've inserted x, y, and z from line into
x(t), y(t), and z(t) from f(x,y,z), respectively.
This equation is a quadratic with respect to t.
So it has either 0 or 1 or 2 roots.
Pictorially, it looks like this.
It's very similar to the case of a line-circle intersection.