In this part, we're going to introduce the Shader class
to make life easier for you.
There's a very unique approach to vector
in GLSL language to the Shader source.
You can name your component
XYZW or RGBA or STPQ.
This mechanism is called swizzling.
So let's consider, for example, vec3 v3  (2,3, 4)
When you create 2D vector
by just assigning X and Y components of v3 using v2 = v3.xy
v2 is now 2D vector (2, 3).
Similarly, you can assign v4 = v3.xxyz,
and then v4 become a 4D vector (2, 2, 3, 4).
Similarly, we can use RGBA, STPQ,
RGBA represents the color components. the texture
STPQ represents texture coordinates we will learn later.
But there's no difference between XYZW, RGBA, STPQ,
it's just a semantic difference.
Bear in mind, you can't use them in a hybrid.
For example, v3.xgbq is not allowed.
When we initialize the vector
we can use the constructors.
We can also initialize the vectors using swizzling.
So you can define a new 4D vector
by combining v4.XYZ with the last field 2.
The vertex attribute is going to have a different value
for each vertex.
But the uniform variable is going to be the same
for all vertex.
So there's two steps to deliver that value
to the uniform variable.
First of all glGetUniformLocation()  identifies
the location of the uniform variable with a specific name.
In this example, it's identifying a uniform
variable location called "outcolor".
Once figured out the location, we use glUniform4f)
to pass the value to that location.
Here, we're passing the 4 float values
because Outcolor is the 4D vector for the rgba.
So in our example, we're receiving the uniform
ourColor value at the fragment shader.
Uniform variable doesn't display in/out
as opposed to attribute variables.
Then we assign the uniform variable to FragColor
to determine the pixel color.
So if we look at this in a diagram,
the attributes are passed from application into the vertex shader
the uniform color is passed into the fragment shader.
GL_Position calculated in the vertex shader and
FragColor calculated in the fragment shader
are passing into H/W, finally,the pixel appears on the screen.
Uniform variable is not always passed
into the fragment shader.
It's going to be delivered to vertex shader as we need it
to be delivered to vertex shader.
But in the case of attribute variable,
it's only passed to the vertex shader.
07_ShaderClass has some other features
that are different.
Inside of that triangle, it's been color interpolated,
so we've got mixes of three different colors at three vertices.
It also uses a timer to loop through
the triangle darkening and lightening.
We also create and use shader classes
to simplify the complex commands involved in creating and using shaders.
The Shader class is defined inside
"shader.h" in the utils folder.
The entire class is embedded in the header file
so we just need to include the header file.
The Shader class is responsible for
reading in the shader file source,
compiling, linking, and creating the shader object.
It also provides functions
to make it easy to pass uniform variables to the shader.
We created the Shader class to simplify
the complex shader setup tasks we've been doing.
The Shader class stores the ID
of the created shader program object.
It also has a constructor that takes
vertex and fragment shader file names as parameters.
This constructor is typically used to initialize the shader.
If we don't call the constructor, we can use initShader()
to load the vertex and fragment shader files.
The use() function calls glUseProgram()
to make this shader available for subsequent renders.
There are other utility functions
that allow us to pass in uniform variables.
A constructor can be used
to generate shader objects
while loading shader files.
This constructor will read in the shader file,
create the shader objects,
create the shader program object,
and do all the initialization.
we can also use the initShader function
as a function that does the same thing.
When using the Shader class, we call the use() function
and then bind and draw the appropriate VAOs
When passing a uniform variable to a shader,
finding its location and passing a value
can be accomplished with a single function.
There are several functions for different types of variables:
setFloat, setBool, setInt, setVec2, setVec3,
setVec4, setMat2, setMat3, setMat4, etc.
Starting with this example, the vertex shader
and fragment shader are stored in different files.
Here, they are saved as 3.3.shader.vs
and 3.3.shader.fs.
Two attribute variables have been defined
in the vertex shader to store the position and color attributes.
The uniform variable, val,
is passed in from the OpenGL application program.
ourColor is a four-dimensional RGBA color vector.
The value of val is multiplied by each component of ourColor
and passed to the fragment shader.
In the fragment shader, ourColor is
assigned to the FragColor output variable as is.
In the Vertex attribute data, the position coordinates
are immediately followed by
the colors of each vertex as RGB values.
we may recall that
VBOs don't have a fixed format.
As such, the format of a VBO can vary from time to time.
We now have alternating position and color
stored in one VBO.
This means that the position (x, y, z) corresponding to
vertex1 is stored, followed by the color (r, g, b) of vertex1.
The position attributes have a starting offset of 0.
This means that they start at the beginning of the VBO.
The stride, spacing between subsequent positions, is 24.
This is because the float value is 4 bytes, and six floats,
three each for position and color, occupy a single vertex area.
The color attribute, on the other hand, starts at offset = 12.
Because the first 12 bytes are occupied by
the position of vertex 1.
The stride of the colors is also 24.
To pass the Position attribute,
we use glVertexAttribPointers() and glEnableVertexAttrib,
where the offset specified is 0, as seen above.
The stride is 6 * sizeof(float) = 6 * 4 = 24.
Secondly, the color attribute starts
after the position at tribute,
so its offset is 3 * 4 = 12.
The sride of the color attribute is also 24.
The colors of the pixels inside the triangle
are computed as an interpolation of the three vertex colors.
This interpolation is calculated based on
the pixel positions obtained in the rasterization stage.
Let the coordinates of the three vertices be
(x1, y1), (x2, y2), and (x3, y3), respectively.
And let the colors given to the three vertices be
c1, c2, and c3, respectively.
In the figure, the color at pixel (x4, y4) is computed as follows.
That is, it is proportional to the relative position of (x4, y4)
on the line segment with (x1, y1) and (x2, y2) as the two endpoints.
Similarly, the color of pixel (x5, y5) is computed
as an interpolation of (x1, y1) and (x3, y3).
Finally, the color of pixel (x6, y6) can be computed
as an interpolation of (x4, y4) and (x5, y5).
Now let's look at the part where we change
the color of the triangle over time.
We want to determine the color using the sin(t) function
computed for the time change t,
so we included the cmath header file
where the sin function is defined.
We use glfwGetTime
to get the current time provided by GLFW.
This function takes in the time that has passed
since the program started as timeValue, a float value in seconds.
The value of sin(timeValue) ranges from -1 to 1.
to make it in the range [0, 1], we divide the timeValue value in half
and add 0.5 to it
Now we can pass the calculated color
to the vertex shader as a uniform variable.