We're going to look at keyboard input and
mouse input that GLFW handles for us.
The guide to GLFW's input
is going to be visible in the document page.
There are two ways that we can do
input processing on GLFW.
One is to register a callback function
so that when that input comes in,
the callback function automatically runs.
The other one is to use functions that start with glfwget...
to read the input state at that moment.
So one of the more stable ways to do this
is using  callback,
but in some cases
it's a little bit more comfortable
to just use GLFWGet.
For example, glfwGetCursorPos,
which returns
the current mouse position.
The glfwSetKeyCallback is a function
that register a callback function. You can specify
the appropriate callback function name in key_callback.
So when the callback function calls,
it's going to give us a macro, a constant, which represents a key,
and an action as a parameter.
Key macro is well listed in this document page on GLFW
so please refer to it.
There are three actions. GLFW_PRESS, as soon as key is pressed,
GLFW_REPEAT occurs when the key is held down,
and GLFW_RELEASE happens as soon as key is released.
glfwGetKey is checking whether the keyboard input happened
or not by the calling from the application program itself.
The key parameter indicates the key the program wants to check,
and the return value is an integer
that is either GLFW_PRESS or GLFW_RELEASE (no GLFW_REPEAT).
In this example program, we want to check
if the 'f' key is pressed and do something.
The glfwSetCursorPosCallback is a call repeated continuously
when the position of the mouse cursor changes,
that is, when the mouse is moving.
It returns (xpos, ypos) as a pair of double values,
represented as screen coordinates.
The screen coordinates are the space where the top left is (0,0)
and the bottom right is the display's resolution.
One thing to remember is that this event will continue to fire
regardless of whether the mouse button is pressed or not.
Also, (xpos, ypos) is returned regardless of
whether the mouse cursor is inside the drawing window or not.
Calling the glfwGetCursorPos function returns
the position of the current mouse cursor.
There are events occurring when Cursor enters and exits a window.
These events are also known as window focus/unfocus.
In the callback, entered is a boolean variable that,
if true, is fired when the cursor enters the window,
and if false, is fired when it exits.
glfwSetMouseButtonCallback occurs
when the mouse button is pressed or released.
Timer functions include glfwGetTime (), which returns
the elapsed time in seconds
since glfw was first initialized.
Because it returns a double value,
we can get a precise time value.
You can use glfwSetTime
to set the timer to the time you want.
Now let's look at a program using the 'f' key to flip the triangle
and change the color with r, g, b keys.
In vertex shader, aPos is passed
as vertex position attribute as before,
and another uniform variable named multY is received.
MultY is 1 or -1,
multiplied by the y coordinate of the vertex,
and when it is -1, the triangle is flipped upside down.
Fragment shaders are the same as before.
The outColor is not received from the vertex shader,
but is passed directly from the application program to the uniform.
The global variables of the application program are
bool type verticalFlip,
colorR, colorG, colorB representing the color of the triangle.
Keyboard callback function key_callback is registered.
When f key is pressed on key_callback,
verticalFlip is toggled to true and false.
When r key is pressed, colorR = 1.0,
and colorG and colorB are set to 0.
Likewise, when g and b keys are pressed.
Check the verticalFlip
before rendering the triangle in the main loop,
passing a multY uniform variable as a -1 value if true.
If it is false, just pass 1.
In addition, as the Fragment shader, the color of the triangle
is passed directly as a uniform variable outColor.
Because outColor is a 4D vector that represents RGBA,
we pass 1.0 along with colorR, colorG, and colorB.
Program 11_Polyline will enter the points one by one
by pressing the left mouse button.
The line segments connecting the input points are displayed.
The last line segment changes continuously
according to the position of the candidate point to be newly input,
so that the line segment to be input can be predicted.
don't need to hold down the left mouse button after entering a point.
If you press'r' key, all input points disappear and reset.
As the color of the input points continues to change,
the color of the line segment that connects the points
interpolates the color of the endpoints.
Let's take a look at the Global variables.
The number of vertices that can be entered is MAX_VERTEX = 200.
Since we want to represent the Position attribute in 3D coordinates,
the size of the vertex position attribute data,
MAX_VERTEX_SIZE, is MAX_VERTEX * 3.
Since we want to represent the Color attribute in RGBA,
the size of the color attribute data is
MAX_COLOR_SIZE = MAX_VERTEX * 4.
nPoint will store the number of points currently entered.
The initial value is 0.
stopInput will become true when the right mouse button is pressed,
preventing further input.
nextPoint serves to allow one more point
to be entered when the mouse cursor starts moving.
VBO[0] and VBO[1] are
two buffers for position and color, respectively.
vertices stores the position data,
which holds the vertices entered so far.
colors will hold the color of each input vertex.
colorOriginal is the six default colors,
and points will be assigned a color in the order they come in.
We need a Keyboard input callback that accepts the key 'r'.
We also specified a CursorPosCallback to catch mouse movement
and a MouseButtonCallback
to accept the left and right mouse buttons.
Let's look at the part of the program that defines VAO and VBO.
There are two VBOs (VBO [0], VBO [1]) in one VAO.
VBO [0] has 3D coordinates as position attribute.
VBO [1] has RGBA (4D) as the color attribute.
VBO [0] is associated with attribute id = 0.
VBO [1] is associated with attribute id = 1.
When the key 'r' comes in, set nPoints = 0
and initialize both stopInput and nextInput.
In other words, go back to the initial state of  no input at all.
So if the left mouse button is pressed,
if stopInput is true, we don't accept no more input
we get the point input when stopInput = false
get the current mouse position
(xpos, ypos) using glfwGetCursorPos
convert (xpos, ypos) into the coordinates in space [-1, 1]
by normalizing it using normalize_cursor_position function.
And then update the position attribute
in VBO[0].
Specifically if nPoints = 0, we make nPoints = 1,
to make the state as other usual ones.
Let's consider when right mouse button pressed.
Again, we only want to add the last point
if stop input is false.
And make stopInput to be true.
The Y at the screen coordinates increases from 0 to SCR_HEIGHT,
from top to bottom.
and x increases from 0 to SCR_WIDTH, left to right.
we want to change it to OpenGL's NDC (-1,-1) ~ (1,1).
First x coords. of screen coordinates into [0, 1]
by (x / SCR_WIDTH),
Double it, subtract one,
then it converts between [-1, 1].
In the case of Y Coordinates, we can follow a similar process,
and multiply the result by -1 to change the number up and down.
So update_vb_vertex is what we're going to do
when a new vertex comes in,
it's going to update the existing VBO at vIndex.
The glBufferSubData is going to update just a portion of VBO.
set the offset (Starting) vIndex * sizeof(float) *3.
That's the last position where the current data in VBO ended.
we're going to add just one point at the  offset
And the size of the data to be added is  sizeof(float) * 3.
Finally the new data to be added
is n[3] which is the coordinates of the new point to be added.
In the rendering part,
we draw the GL_LINE_STRIP of size nPoints
to draw the line strip which is currently inputted.