Let's start the lecture on Transformations.
Frame has a set v that form the axis,
and origin P0.
We express the frame as (v1,v2,v3,P0)=(v,P0).
Point P is uniquely expressed
using a frame as P = P0 + b^T v.
Here b = (beta1, beta2, beta3)
are the coordinates of point P with respect to frame (v, P0).
In the case of point P, because it has a fixed position,
it cannot be expressed using only the basis.
It can be expressed as a frame with the origin added to the basis.
Now let's learn about
some basic transformations used in 3D.
First, translation (parallel movement).
This refers to a case where a point P is translated by d
and moved to P'.
If all vertices forming one 3D object
are translated by d,
the object itself will naturally be translated by d.
Let’s express the translation in matrix form.
Both the original point p and the translated position p' are
expressed as 4D vectors that are homogenous coordinates.
At this time, the 4 x 4 matrix T(ax,ay,az) is defined like this,
where d=(ax,ay,az) is the translation factor.
Look closely, the translation factors ax, ay, and az are arranged
in order in the rightmost column of the identity matrix.
By calculating Tp
by multiplying this translation matrix T
by the original point p, we get p'.
This fits the definition of translation well.
In the future, we will often see translation
operation and translation matrix T
being used interchangeably.
Then, consider the case of translating once as d=(ax,ay,az)
and then translating as -d=(-ax,-ay,-az) back again.
Point p is translated by d and goes to p',
and then translated by -d and returns to p.
Since p' = Tp, if both sides are multiplied
by the inverse matrix of T, T^(-1), p = T^(-1)p'.
In other words, the inverse translation matrix is
the inverse matrix of the original translation matrix T.
Then, what is the  translation matrix
with the translation factor -d,
representing the inverse translation of the original translation?
This is the same as the inverse matrix of T, T^(-1),
and if you solve for it, you get the formula:
This is exactly the case when -d = (-ax,-ay,-az)
which was created by creating the translation
matrix we defined.
This time we will define rotation,
but to simplify the explanation,
we will first look at the case of 2D rotation.
Let's call the point
that appears when the 2D point (x, y) is rotated
counterclockwise by theta as (x',y').
At this time, the original x can be expressed as rho
cos(phi) and y can be expressed as rho sin(phi).
Here rho is the distance from the origin to (x,y),
which, as we well know,
is the square root of (x^2 + y^2).
The results x' and y' after rotating by theta
can be expressed as rho cos(theta+phi)
and rho sin(theta + phi), respectively.
Using the sine and cosine formulas,
x' and y' can each be expressed like this.
Here, if you replace rho cos(phi) and rho sin(phi) with x and y,
you get an equation like this.
This will be the formula to find the result
(x',y') when (x,y) is rotated by theta.
Finally, if we organize this equation in matrix form,
it looks like this.
Here, the 2 x 2 matrix made up of cosine and sine
becomes the matrix of 2D rotation.
Now we want to see the 3D case.
and define rotation in 3D.
For rotations in 2D, the axis of rotation was always (0,0,1),
i.e. the z-axis.
However, in 3D an infinite number of rotation
axes are possible.
First, if you define 3D rotation
with respect to the z-axis
used in 2D, it becomes this equation.
If we rotate (x,y,z) about the z-axis
by theta, x' and y' remain the same as when rotated in 2D,
and z' remains the same as z.
Because the z-axis is the axis of rotation,
if you rotate any point about the z-axis,
the z-coordinate does not change
because the rotation occurs in the xy-plane,
which is perpendicular to the z-axis.
Using a matrix, this can be expressed as p' = Rz p.
Here, Rz(theta) is
a 4 x 4 rotation matrix that represents
rotation by theta about the z axis.
If you look closely, the 2 x 2 part in the top left of Rz(theta)
is the same as the 2D rotation matrix we saw in the previous slide.
The remaining part is in the form of a general transformation matrix
where only the diagonal elements are 1.
Then, why is the rotation matrix in 3D
expressed as a 4 x 4 matrix instead of 3 x 3?
This is because of the translation matrix explained earlier.
As we saw earlier, the translation
matrix cannot be expressed as a 3 x 3
matrix, and homogenous coordinates must be used.
From the perspective of data structure,
if all transformation matrices should be expressed as one type,
This is why we use a 4 x 4 matrix rather than a 3 x 3 matrix.
Now let's look at the rotation about the x and y axes.
First, the rotation matrix Rx(theta) about the x-axis is expressed like this.
If you look closely, the 2 x 2 rotation part is centered in
the center of the matrix.
Similarly, the rotation matrix about the y axis looks like this.
Let's say we obtain (x',y') by applying rotation transformation
R(theta), which rotates by theta, to (x,y).
Now let's look at the reverse transformation R^(-1)(theta),
which returns from (x',y') back to (x,y).
Conceptually, R^(-1) is the same as R(-theta).
In other words, after rotating by theta,
the rotation back to the original position is rotated by -theta.
We used cos(theta) and sin(theta)
values for rotations about the x, y, and z axes.
If you replace -theta with theta in this equation,
cos(-theta) is the same as cos(theta), and
sin(-theta) is the same as -sin(theta).
So, the matrix of
R(-theta) can be easily obtained by slightly changing R(theta).
In other words, R^(-1) is the inverse matrix of R.
However, if you actually calculate R^(-1), it comes out the same as R^T.
Transpose of a matrix refers to an operation that changes the rows
and columns of a matrix.
In summary, when R is given,
R^(-1),R(-theta), and R^T are all equal.
Rotation and translation during transformation
are called
rigid transformation or rigid-body transformation.
This means that rotation and translation do not change
the shape or size of the object being transformed,
regardless of how many times it is repeated and in what order.
Looking at the picture, reflection transformation
also belongs to rigid transformation.
Reflection is a transformation that reflects an object
as if it were reflected in a mirror around a certain reference axis.
Rigid transformation simply changes the location
and orientation of the object.
On the other hand, in the case of non-rigid transformation,
the size and the shape of the object can be changed, such as by distorting it.
Scaling is a transformation that changes the size of an object.
Uniform scaling, which changes the size of an object consistently along all axes,
is also possible, and non-uniform scaling,
which changes the size to an inconsistent size
along the axis directions, is also possible.
Scaling is a type of non-rigid transformation.
Scaling can be thought of
as changing the distance from the origin to point (x,y,z).
The formula for changing the distance to x by beta_x times,
the distance to y by beta_y times, and the distance to z by beta_z times is as follows.
Here (beta_x, beta_y, beta_z) is called the scaling factor.
For example, if beta_x is set to 0.5, the distance in the x direction will be half the original distance.
If beta_x, beta_y, and beta_z are all the same value,
uniform scaling occurs.
Otherwise, non-uniform scaling occurs.
When expressing scaling transformation like p' = Sp,
matrix S is a 4x4 scaling
matrix, and beta_x, beta_y, and beta_z are located in the diagonal elements.
Assume that (x, y) is scaled by (beta_x, beta_y, beta_z)
and sent to (x', y').
At this time, inverse scaling S^(-1), which returns (x', y') back to (x, y),
takes S(1/beta_x, 1/beta_y, 1/beta_z), that is,
the reciprocal of the scaling factor. It's possible.
Even without detailed explanation, you can intuitively understand why.
Shearing transformation serves to tilt
and distort the original object
as shown in the picture.
To see this in more detail, let's look at a cross section in the xy plane.
In the picture, we are translating the point (x,y) to (x',y').
As the y value increases, the amount of movement increases,
which ultimately has the effect of tilting and distorting the object
by the angle of theta.
At the base of the square,
you can see that the original base remains the same because y = 0.
If this is expressed as a trigonometric function,
tangent theta can be expressed as y'/(x'-x) or y/(x'-x) by definition.
cotangent theta is the reciprocal of tangent theta,
so it is (x'-x)/y.
From this, x' = x + y
cot(theta), y'= y, and since it only moves in the x direction, z' doesn't change.
If this is expressed as an x-shearing matrix Hx(theta),
it becomes this equation.
And, Hx^(-1)(theta), which is the inverse of Hx(theta),
is the same as Hx(-theta).
The y-shearing and z-shearing
transformations can be easily derived
using methods similar to this derivation process.
I encourage you to try these yourself.
Let us assume that P is transformed into P' by M1,
and P' is transformed into P'' by M2.
These two equations can be combined to write P'' = M2 M1 P.
If the product of M2 M1 is called M3
matrix, P'' can be expressed as M3 P.
At this time, M3 is called the matrix of composite transformation.
One thing to note
is that composite transformation does not follow commutative laws.
In other words, M2 M1 and M1 M2 do not represent the same transformation.
This is also a general property of matrix multiplication.
For example, in this picture, P is first rotated by 90 degrees
and transformed into P', then translated again by (3,3),
and finally, P'' = (2, 6).
However, if you do translation (3,3) first and then rotate 90 degrees,
you will get a completely different result, P''=(-4,6).
In other words, when considering composite transformation, you must pay attention to the order of transformations.
For an explanation of matrix multiplication, please see this URL.
Let’s learn more about the properties of the rotation matrix.
The 4x4 rotation matrix R in 3D is defined like this.
We only considered rotation about the basic axes x, y, and z, but in fact
there are infinitely many vectors that can be rotation axes in 3D.
Considering these general rotation axes,
the general form of the rotation matrix is expressed as this equation.
In particular, rotation uses only the 3x3 portion in the upper left of the 4x4 matrix.
So, let’s consider only this 3x3 part by separating it into an R-hat matrix.
R-hat has the following properties.
First, all row vectors are perpendicular to each other.
All column vectors are also perpendicular to each other.
And, if you multiply R-hat and the transpose of R-hat,
you get the identity matrix.
As a result, you can see that
the transpose of R-hat is the same as the inverse of R-hat.
In general, finding an inverse matrix is quite complicated,
but it can be done simply by transposing, which is very convenient.
A matrix that satisfies the three properties
up to this point is called an “orthogonal matrix.”
As mentioned earlier, R-hat has one more property.
The property is that all row vectors and column
vectors are unit vectors.
A matrix that satisfies all four properties
is called an “orthonormal matrix” and is a correct rotation
matrix that maintains the properties of rigid transformation.
The 4x4 rotation matrix R looks like this.
Translation matrix T has this form.
Now let's consider a composite transformation that performs rotation
first and then translation.
The matrix M of this composite transformation is the product of T and R.
If rotation is applied to point p first,
it becomes Rp, and if translation is applied to Rp, it becomes TRp, so M = TR.
We have already explained previously
that the order of matrix multiplication should not be changed.
If you look closely at the calculated M,
the rotation matrix is still there in the 3x3 part at the top left,
On the other hand, you can see that
the translation factors remain the same in the rightmost column.
If you actually do this matrix multiplication TR, you will get something like this.
So, you can see that
the matrix of the composite transformation of “translation
after rotation” can be easily found
without actually calculating the product of the matrices.
As an example of a composite transformation,
let's consider rotation about an arbitrary point other than the origin.
In the picture, the gray triangle has been transformed into a yellow triangle
by rotating 90 degrees about the red point P = (x1, y1).
The rotations we have considered so far have all been rotations about the origin.
To use that rotation, we first apply T1(-x1, -y1) to the triangle,
which translates P to the origin.
Then we apply rotation R(theta) about the origin.
Finally, apply T2(x1, y1)
which translates the origin back to the original P.
The composite transformation that combines all three stages of transformation
is T2 R T1.
Let's consider two different frames
(v1, v2, v3, P0) and (u1, u2, u3, Q0).
The first frame is a frame with P0
as the origin and (v1, v2, v3) as the three axes, that is, basis vectors.
Likewise, the second frame is a frame with Q0 as the origin and (u1, u2,
u3) as the basis vector.
Among them, if frame (u1,
u2, u3, Q0) is expressed in relation to another frame
(v1, v2, v3, P0), it can be expressed as this equation.
In other words, the u1, u2,
u3 vectors can each be expressed as coordinates on the basis
(v1, v2, v3), and since Q0 is a point,
it can be expressed like this regarding the frame (v1, v2, v3, P0).
These equations are organized in matrix form.
That is, (u1, u2, u3, Q0)
can be expressed as the product of M and (v1, v2, v3, P0).
Here, M is a 4 x 4 matrix that contains the coordinates of (v1, v2, v3, P0)
of u1, u2, u3, and Q0.
Matrix M is called “matrix of change of frames”.
In other words, it is a matrix that changes the first frame to the second frame.
Let us assume that the coordinates of point P in frames G and F
are a and b, respectively.
If you recall from the beginning of this note
where we expressed the coordinates of a point in a given frame, p can first be written
as b^T times F with respect to the F frame.
Likewise, if we express p in terms of the G frame, we get a^T times G.
If there is a transformation M that changes b^T to a^T, then
b^T times M will be equal to a^T, so it can be expressed like this.
To rewrite it, a^T = b^T M.
If you transpose both sides, it becomes like this:
If you solve this, it becomes a = M^T b.
For reference, the transpose of XY
multiplied by two matrices is the transpose of Y multiplied by the transpose of X.
Here, M^T can be seen as a transformation
matrix that converts coordinates from frame
F to G.
Here, to convert the coordinates in the opposite direction,
that is, from frame G to F,
you can apply the inverse of M^T.
Here, let's denote the inverse of M^T as matrix T.
When I try to explain it this way, I don’t really get the hang of it.
Let's look at a real example.
First, consider two different frames G and F.
Let's call the coordinates of a point in those two frames a and b, respectively.
Since we said that a = Cb, C is the coordinates conversion
matrix that goes from b (i.e.
in frame F) to a (i.e. in frame G).
In the previous slide, C was expressed as M^T.
The problem is how to find this C.
As shown in the figure,
let's assume that we can represent frame G in frame F.
In the picture, the x-axis of G is represented by a unit vector u in F, and the
y-axis is represented by a unit vector v in F.
Also, let's assume that the origin of the G frame becomes point
p when expressed in terms of the F frame.
At this time, let's consider C's inverse first.
This is a matrix that converts the coordinates of G to F.
In the previous slide, the inverse of C was indicated as T.
Since T is a matrix that converts G to F, if
the x-axis of G (1, 0, 0) is converted to T, u comes out.
Recall that in the previous slide we assumed that
the x-axis of G is expressed as u in the F frame.
Here, the x-axis of G is indicated as (1, 0, 0, 0) in homogenous expression.
In fact, the part of T that is contributed by the transformation results of the x, y, and z axes of G is the 3 x 3 part in the upper left corner,
which is the rotation part of the 4 x 4 matrix.
Therefore, we set the w value to 0.
Likewise, if you transform the y-axis of G (0, 1,
0) to T, you will get v.
Also, if you convert the z-axis of G (0, 0, 1) to T, you will get n.
Finally, if we convert (0, 0, 0), the origin of G, to T, we get p.
Here, the origin and p are both points, not axes, so set w = 1.
Now, if we collect all these results and get the T matrix, it looks like this.
Looking at the T matrix, the u, v, and n vectors
are written in the 1st, 2nd, and 3rd columns, respectively,
and the coordinates of the origin p are placed in the last column.
However, this form is something we see a lot.
It is a form of composite transformation
matrix of “translation after rotation”.
That is, when the unit vectors of the three basic axes of G in the F frame are u, v, and n,
Create a 3x3 rotation matrix with three columns of the three vectors and place them in
the upper left 3x3 part of F.
And just make the coordinates of the origin of G in the F frame
the translation part of T.
In other words, the T matrix that converts G to F is the product of the translation
matrix and rotation matrix created as above.
In summary, if any frame G can be expressed in terms of a reference frame F,
we can easily create a T matrix
that converts the coordinates of G to the coordinates of F like this.
So, in the opposite case, that is,
how do we find matrix C that converts F to G?
C can be found by calculating the inverse of T.
However, it is said that T is the product of the translation matrix and rotation matrix.
Here, let's express the translation matrix as H and the rotation matrix as K.
Then C, which is the inverse of T, becomes the product of the inverse of K
and the inverse of H.
As we said earlier that the rotation matrix is orthonormal
and its inverse is the same as transpose,
the inverse of K can be obtained by simply transposing K.
Also, the inverse of translation matrix H can be easily obtained
because it represents translation in the opposite direction of the translation
factor (p_1, p_2, p_3).
In other words, to find C, it is much simpler to inverse
H and K separately before multiplying HK to calculate T.
Now that we know how
to obtain the matrix of change of frame in both directions,
let's solve the actual problem.
To simplify the calculation, we will describe it as a two-dimensional problem.
First, the unit vector u representing the x-axis of G in the F frame
is (2 / root(5), 1 / root(5)).
Also, the unit vector v representing the y-axis of G in the F frame
is (-1 / root(5), 2 / root(5)).
In fact, you can see that these numbers are correct
if you calculate them by counting the graduations of the 2D grid in the picture.
Also, if the origin of G is expressed in the F frame, p = (3, 2).
Now we want to find matrix T that converts G to F.
As seen in the previous slide, T is the product of the translation
matrix created using p and the rotation matrix created using u and v.
That is, T is expressed in this way.
Now, in the opposite direction, that is, matrix C,
which converts F to G, just needs to find the inverse of T.
By using T = Tp R, I think I can find the inverse more easily.
(Tp R)^(-1) is R^(-1) Tp^(-1).
This can be expressed as an equation:
Finally, multiplying the two inverse matrices
gives us the C matrix.
Now, to convert the point q = (4,
5) expressed in terms of F frame to coordinates in terms of G frame,
we just need to calculate the product of C and q.
When I calculated it, I got (2.236, 2.236).
Looking at the G frame in the picture as a standard, it seems to be roughly correct.