Let’s start the UsingGLM lecture.
GLM is a useful library
used to facilitate vector and matrix operations
in OpenGL.
In fact, programmers can create
and use vector or matrix classes themselves,
but since GLM is a proven library,
we will use it.
GLM is widely used to implement
not only OpenGL
but also many applications
that require a linear system.
Since GLM is fully implemented in the header file,
you only need to include the necessary header files,
and separate processes
such as linking or compiling are not required.
We already have GLM installed.
So, just include the header files similar to this example.
Let's look briefly at an example using GLM.
glm::vec4 is a 4D vector type
and can be initialized like this.
glm::mat4 is a 4x4 matrix type,
which can be used to represent the transformation matrices
we want to use.
When initializing, if you enter only one value, 1.0,
it will be initialized as an identity matrix.
If you enter only one value other than 1,
it becomes a matrix that places that value
in the diagonal elements.
In order to multiply matrices for composite transformation,
a matrix called trans is first initialized as an identity matrix.
The glm::translate function creates a translation matrix
that translates by the following parameter,
vec3(1, 1, 0), and returns it.
Now trans has become a translation matrix.
To actually translate the coordinates of a vector (or point),
simply multiply trans and vector.
Here, (1, 0, 0) is translated by (1, 1, 0),
so (2, 1, 0) comes out.
This time, it is a case of applying scaling and rotation.
First, prepare identity matrix I as in the previous example.
Next, multiply I by a rotation
matrix that rotates 90 degrees to obtain the IR matrix.
The last parameter of the rotate function is the z-axis, the rotation axis.
Calculate the IRS matrix by multiplying IR by the scale matrix.
Multiply IRS and vector v to scale and rotate v.
The order of applying transformation is to scale first and then rotate.
This time, we will change the position of the vertex
using the transformation
matrix passed from the application program to the shader.
A 4x4 matrix called uniform mat4 transform was passed to the shader.
The final vertex position
gl_Position is calculated by multiplying the transform
matrix and aPos vector.
In the previous slides, the position of the transformed vertex
within the application program was calculated.
However, a more commonly used method is to pass the matrix
and original vertex positions separately
and multiply them in the shader, as in this example.
In this way, it is possible to transmit the original
vertex position to the GPU only once,
and update it with the transformed position by transmitting only the matrix again
each time the transformation changes.
This code shows
the process of transferring the transformation
matrix from the application program to the shader.
First, find the location of the shader's uniform
variable named "transform".
The glGetUniformLocation function is used in this process.
Then pass the matrix using glUniformMatrix4fv.
transformLoc is the location we found earlier.
1 is the number of matrices to be transmitted.
The next one is the transpose option.
When transposing a Matrix, use GL_TRUE.
Here we don't need to transpose
so we just use GL_FALSE.
The last parameter is the matrix variable to be passed.
To convert from GLM format to GLSL format,
matrix trans was passed by wrapping it in glm::value_ptr.
In this program, after creating a box,
we will apply the transformations of scale,
rotate, and translate to it as a composite transformation.
The transformation matrices required in the render
function are multiplied.
First, create an identity matrix
and multiply it by the translate, rotate, and scale matrices in order.
As mentioned several times, the order
in which matrices are multiplied is opposite to the order in which transformations are applied.
Once the matrix is calculated, we pass it to the shader.
After that, you can render VAO.
Let's try some experiments.
In this example, we initially initialized the transformation
matrix to identity
and did not add any other transformations.
In this case, none of the scale,
rotation, or translation are applied,
so the box is larger than the previous program, does not rotate,
and its center is located in the middle of the screen.
In this case, only scale is applied.
Rotation and translation were not performed.
In this case, rotation and scale are applied.
Because no translation has been applied,
the rotating box is in the center of the screen.
In this case, scale, rotation, and translation are all applied.
In this example, the order of applying scale
first and then rotation and translation was changed.
If you translate first and then rotate,
the box will draw a large circle at the translated position
and rotate around the origin.
However, if rotation is applied first and then translation is performed,
the box will first rotate on its own
based on the center of the box at the origin, producing the effect of translation.
Please watch the videos and see the differences.
In this program, the two squares have different scales
and rotate at different speeds.
Speed1 and speed2 are defined as global variables.
Speed1 represents 90 degrees per second,
and speed2 represents 45 degrees per second.
In the rendering part, the first thing to do is to draw a red square in the upper left corner.
Create a composite transformation matrix by multiplying the scale,
rotate, and translation matrices.
We used speed1 to calculate the rotation angle.
Also, the scale was set to 0.5 in all x, y, and z axes.
Then, the calculated transformation matrix and color (red)
were passed to the shader as uniform variables.
It is simple to use the set function provided by the Shader object.
After that, you can draw VAO.
This is the part where you draw the second square.
Non-uniform scaling was applied to the second rectangle,
and it was scaled by 0.3, 0.5, and 1.0 times in the x, y, and z directions, respectively.
Yellow color has been sent to the shader