Let's start the lecture on Quaternion.
One of the efficient
and stable ways to calculate rotation in 3D
is to use quaternion.
Quaternion is a 4-dimensional vector (q0, q1, q2, q3),
which can be seen as consisting of one scalar q0
and one 3D vector
q = (q1, q2, q3).
Quaternion theory has many complexities,
but in our course we will introduce
only the bare minimum that will be used to calculate rotation.
First, we are given two quaternions a = (q0,q) and b = (p0 p).
The sum of two quaternions
a + b is the sum of normal 4D vectors,
and is calculated by adding the corresponding elements.
The product ab of two quaternions
is calculated as the equation given here.
Here, the dot product and cross product of the 3D vectors
q and p included in a and b were used.
Quaternion size (magnitude, size)
is the size of a normal 4D vector.
The inverse a^(-1) for Quaternion multiplication
is defined as this equation.
The product of a and a^(-1) gives the identity (1, 0) for multiplication.
You can use quternion to rotate a 3D point
about an arbitrary axis.
First, create quaternio p = (0, u) with the 3D point
u = (x,y,z) to be rotated.
Rotation axis is given as unit vector v.
Now let’s look at how to find u’,
which is the result of rotating u about the v-axis by theta, i.e.
u’ = 𝑅_𝑣(𝜃)𝑢. First, create a unit quaternion r:
And we define the inverse of r as follows:
The inverse of r is also a unit quaternion.
Then p’ = (0, u’) is obtained by the equation:
p’ = r p r^(-1) Conversion
between quaternion and rotation
matrix forms is possible.
Given that the quaternion r representing rotation is given like this,
the corresponding rotation matrix is given as follows.
The RotAxis program creates a 3D cube
and rotates it about a random axis.
If you press q on the keyboard,
rotation will be calculated using quaternion,
and if you press m, it will be calculated using matrix.
In reality, there is no difference between the two methods,
so there is no loss of rotation when the method is changed.
GLM supports quaternion functions.
To use them, include the header file above.
In this program, you will draw a cube, a 3D object, for the first time.
Since we will continue to use cubes many times in the future,
we have defined a Cube class that will be used to create and draw cubes.
It is contained in cube.h in the utils folder,
and all implementations are included in the header.
In the Cube class, data such as the coordinates
of vertices for the cube object are already defined.
Cube vertex position has three coordinates of x, y, and z for four vertices
on each of the six faces,
so a total of 72 (6 x 4 x 3) elements exist in the cubeVertices array.
The default coordinates represent the coordinates of a cube
with the origin as the center
and all edges having a length of 1.
In addition, normal and texture coordinates are data that will be used in the rendering methods
we will learn in the future.
In addition, the colors of the faces are also defined.
cubeIndices defines indices to use
for DrawElements.
In the Cube class, VAO, VBO, and EBO
are defined for drawing a cube.
A default constructor exists so that all necessary
buffers can be created and initialized.
With the second constructor,
you can change the coordinates
by changing the default vertex positions.
The center position of the initially positioned cube
can be changed to (dx,
dy, dz), and the initial size
can be changed by applying uniform scale factor s.
The draw() function draws a cube using the given shader.
The program first defines global variables,
and axis defines the rotation axis around which the cube will rotate.
Here it is given as (1, 1, 1).
Additionally, we defined the initial position of the cube (here
(0.4, 0.4, 0)) and the initial size (here: 0.3).
In main(), we create cube as a constructor.
The rotation axis is normalized to a unit vector in advance.
In the render function,
first prepare a transformation matrix initialized with identity.
If the rotState changed by keyboard input is MAT_ROT,
glm::rotate is used to create a transform matrix.
If rotState is QUAT_ROT, quaternion is used.
The GLM function glm::angleAxis creates a quaternion
corresponding to rotation with the given axis and angle.
You can convert this to a rotation
matrix using the glm::toMat4 function
and use this as a transform matrix.
In the remaining part, the transform matrix is passed to the shader
and the cube is drawn by calling cube->draw().
The vertex shader defines vectors of position,
normal, color, and texture coordinates through which cube class
data is transmitted.
Of course normal and texture coordinates are not used yet.
However, because the Cube class is implemented
to always copy these data to the VBO,
these four attributes must be received from the vertex shader.
This is the toColor out
variable that will be passed to the Fragment shader.
The transform matrix is passed as a uniform variable.
gl_Position is calculated by multiplying the transform
matrix by the original position.