So far we have been using NDC,
or normalized device coordinates.
In NDC, the range of each coordinate in the x, y, and z directions
is limited to -1 to 1.
Objects that are not within this range
become invisible.
However, this limitation is too unrealistic.
From now on, we will be free to freely
decide which space we will use.
And in the vertex shader,
this random space is transformed into NDC
and the resulting gl_position is sent to the hardware.
In the picture, you can see that a light green rectangle
and a yellow quadrant are drawn at the camera boundary
in a user-defined space of size 90x90.
Vertex shader converts this to NDC
between [-1,1] and sends it to HW.
Vertex coordinates are converted through several steps.
Coordinates defined in local space are converted to world space
by applying model transformation
and to view space by applying view transformation.
Additionally, it is converted to clip space through projection transformation,
and then finally converted to screen space
using viewport transformation and displayed on the screen.
Local space, also called object space,
is a coordinate system limited to one specific object.
For example, let's say
you are modeling a cube in graphics software such as Blender.
Usually, a cube initially has a basic shape centered at the origin,
with one edge having a length of 1.
Afterwards, we change its size
or relocate it.
The coordinate system that an object initially uses to define itself
is called local space,
and the coordinates of vertices are called local coordinates.
Objects defined in local space
are gathered in one space to form a scene.
For example, a house, a tree, a car, etc.
all appear in one scene.
Houses, trees, and cars
were all initially modeled in their own local spaces.
At this time, for example, the center of each object would be the origin
and its size would not be relatively adjusted.
These objects must be collected and placed in one space,
and this one space is called world space.
World coordinates refer to coordinates
defined within this world space.
In the picture, the two rectangles that make up the robot's arm
were initially modeled as A and B in each local space.
To move and place them in one world
space, transformation from local to world space is required.
The matrix representing the transformation from local to world
is called the model matrix,
and this transformation is called model transformation.
In the picture, you can see that
the cube is moved from local space
to world space according to model transformation.
Objects in world space
are converted to view space by view transformation.
View space is also called camera space or eye space.
View space is a space defined around the user's view.
In the picture, when objects exist in world space,
the view space is a space that has the center of projection, or COP, as the origin,
which is the location of the camera.
View transformation, expressed as a view
matrix, converts coordinates from world to view space.
Next is the conversion from view space to clip space.
Clip space is defined by clip coordinates,
and these clip coordinates are NDC.
As I've mentioned several times, the final output
gl_Position from the vertex shader must have
NDC coordinates.
In NDC, all coordinates of x,y,z
are in the range of [-1, 1].
All coordinates that do not fall within this
range will not be displayed on the screen.
For example, points like (-2,0,0), (0.2,0.5,-5).
The conversion from view space to clip space
is done by a projection matrix.
In particular, projection transformation can be separated into two steps:
projection and perspective division.
The last remaining step is to convert the clip
space coordinates to screen space
coordinates through viewport transformation.
Screen space is the pixel coordinates that appear on the actual display screen.
In fact, this viewport
transformation occurs automatically by the graphics H/W,
so we don't have to do any programming.
The Model Transformation program shows the process of converting a basic cube
with local coordinates into model transformation,
moving it to world space,
and converting it to NDC coordinates through appropriate view
and projection transformation.
In the vertex shader, vectors of position,
normal, color, and texture coordinates through which Cube class data are transmitted
are defined as attribute variables.
Of course normal and texture coordinates are not used yet.
toColor is an out variable to be passed from the vertex shader
to the fragment shader,
and is passed from the application program to the vertex shader.
gl_Position is calculated by multiplying the original position by the model,
view, and projection matrices in that order.
In the render() function, we create a model, view, and projection
matrix and pass them to the vertex
shader for transformation.
First, initialize the three 4x4 matrices called model,
view, and projection with identity.
For cube animation, find out the current time
and set the shader to use.
The model transformation initially rotates the cube
around the z-axis by an angle
equal to the current time multiplied by rotSpeed.
The top right picture shows the initial position,
the one below it is rotated about the z-axis.
We then rotate the cube by -55 degrees about the x-axis.
This creates a model transformation for the cube,
and animation becomes possible over time.
For view transformation, the camera must be positioned appropriately,
and the glm::lookAt function was used here.
The camera was located at (0, 0, 3), and the point the camera was looking at, that is,
the target point, was set as the origin.
The camera's up vector was set to (0, 1, 0), that is, the Y axis.
How this lookAt function is implemented
will be explained in detail in the next slide.
For reference, OpenGL's default
camera is located at the origin and faces the -Z direction.
Next, the projection matrix has
a convenient function called glm::perspective.
The parameters of this function are FOV (field of view), aspect ratio, near, and far.
A slide will be devoted later
to the implementation of projection transformation
along with their meaning.
Now, pass the model, view,
and projection matrices to the shader in the form of uniform
variables and draw a cube.