In this note, we learn more about the implementation of view transformation,
which converts world space to view space.
Through this process, you can see how
the glm::lookAt function is implemented.
Cameras play an important role in computer graphics.
Even if the same objects are fixed in the 3D world,
the final ouput image will vary
depending on how you look at the objects.
This is similar to how when taking a picture of a person,
depending on the position and direction of the camera,
the picture taken will be different
even if the same person is taken.
The picture shows the game
view and working view of the Unity game engine.
The cameras used for these two views
are different.
Depending on where you place the white camera
in the working view
and where you point it, the actual game scene
shown in the upper game view will vary.
The direction of the white camera icon in the working view
is not the direction the actual camera is facing.
However, it is displayed that way
because the camera icon is fixed in that direction.
Here the camera is looking towards the two spheres,
allowing us to see the game view in the upper window.
As previously mentioned, the camera
in OpenGL is always positioned
at the origin and facing the -z direction.
We cannot change this location and direction.
So how do you move the camera to the desired location and direction
so that you can see the view you want?
It simulates the motion of the camera.
In other words, it makes the object in the current view
feel like the camera is moving by
moving it in the opposite direction of the camera motion.
This is similar to creating a train interior set during a movie
shoot and moving the trees outside the window
to give the impression that the train is moving.
In other words, the idea is to place objects
instead of placing the camera.
To define camera space,
various camera parameters are defined
in world space.
The world coordinate system we are familiar with has as its basis
the x, y, and z axes that are perpendicular to each other,
and is a right-handed coordinate system.
That is, the positive direction of the z-axis
is pointing toward us from the screen.
To define a Camera,
several important parameters are defined.
P is the location of the camera
and is called Center Of Projection, or COP for short.
A represents the target point
the camera is looking at, here we will call it “at point”.
V is the up vector,
which is a vector that represents the direction above
the camera's head, as shown in the picture.
Now, let’s define the view (camera, eye) coordinate system
using the above parameters.
We will find the three axes of this coordinate system, UVN.
U is the right axis vector of the camera,
which corresponds to the x-axis in a general coordinate system.
As defined earlier, V is an axis vector
representing the upward direction of the camera, that is, the y direction.
Lastly, N represents the axis in the direction the camera is facing,
which corresponds to the +z axis of a general coordinate system.
The N vector becomes a vector going from P to A.
Also, N is equal to the normal vector of the view plane.
However, in the picture, the +N direction is opposite to world space,
and the +N direction is toward the inside of the screen from us.
In other words, the view coordinate system
can be said to be a left-handed coordinate system.
Based on this definition of UVN,
we will look at how to obtain the actual UVN in the next slide.
Now let's look at how to calculate UVN axes
from given camera parameters P, A, and V.
First, let's assume that
instead of up vector V, virtual up
vector v' is given as a parameter.
v' is not an exact V direction vector,
but an approximate vector representing the approximate up direction.
In fact, the direction vector from P to A is N, and N
and V must be perpendicular to each other.
However, it is not easy for the user to calculate these vectors
directly and input them as camera parameters.
Therefore, give a roughly similar v' and have the program
calculate the exact V.
In many cases, the y-axis (0, 1,
0) of world space is used as v'.
Of course, if you are holding the camera upside down,
the -y axis may be better.
Calculating N is the easiest.
If the vector A – P going from P to A is small
n, normalizing n becomes N.
The U vector is perpendicular to both V and N.
We cross product n and v' to find small u,
and normalize it to find U.
If you look closely, you can find something strange.
Since it is a UVN coordinate system,
you may be thinking that to find U,
you need to do V x N, not N x V.
But that is the case in right-handed coordinate system.
As seen earlier, camera space UVN is a left-handed coordinate system,
so U was obtained by calculating N x V,
which is the opposite direction of V x N.
Now that N and U are determined,
we can find the exact V.
If you calculate v by doing
u x n and normalize it, you get V.
As above, since the cross product is calculated in the opposite direction to the
right-handed coordinate system, u x n is calculated rather than n x u.
Once the UVN axis of the view space
has been determined, coordinate conversion from world space to view
space is possible.
Now we can determine the view
matrix mentioned in the previous note
05_1_Transformation Pipeline.
First, U, V, and N were obtained using the method described previously.
Additionally, the coordinates of COP P are given.
At this time, all coordinates of P and UVN are expressed
based on world space.
Also, all UVNs are unit vectors.
According to the previously studied change-of-frame, the transformation T_cw,
which converts from view coordinates to world coordinates,
is given like this.
T_cw = T_p R, which is a general “rotation-before-translation”
type matrix that places UVN vectors
and coordinates of P in each column of the matrix.
Since our original goal was "world to view space",
which is the opposite direction to the above,
the T_wc matrix can be obtained by finding the inverse of T_cw like this.
This can be easily understood by remembering that the inverse of a rotation
matrix is the same as the transpose of that matrix, and the inverse of a translation
matrix is simply to reverse the direction of the vector.
Let's look at a real-life example of the process described above.
To simplify calculations, COP, P, is expressed as world coordinates
(0, 0, 5).
That is, it is on the +z axis,
and the camera is currently looking at the origin of world space.
That is, let's assume A = (0, 0, 0).
Also, let's assume that the up vector is just the same as the y-axis.
Please refer to the picture.
First, n = A - P, so N = (0, 0, -1),
In other words, it becomes the -z axis of the world.
Since u = n x v', U = (1, 0, 0), i.e.
equal to the x-axis of the world.
Finally, if we calculate v = u x n, v
becomes the y-axis of the world, as we first assumed.
Now let's convert a point Q_w = (3,
3, -1) in world space into view coordinates.
As derived from the previous slide, view
coordinates Q_c are equal to the product of T_wc
matrix and Q_w.
I'm sure you can all remember this formula.
If you input the UVN and P coordinates calculated in the previous chapter here,
Q_c will be (3, 3, 6, 1).
In fact, this coordinate transformation can be done intuitively
without any calculations.
Since the Camera is at (0, 0, 5) on the world +z axis and facing the origin,
the z coordinate -1 of Q_w will be 6 in Q_c.
It will also be easy to understand
that the remaining U and V remain unchanged at 3.
In this example, we slightly changed the coordinates of COP to (1, -1, 5).
This will slightly distort the view
space and change the N, U, and V axes.
The calculation method is the same as before.
The function that calculates the transformation
matrix that converts from world to view space through
this process is glm::lookAt.
Parameters are given as COP (P), target
(A), and virtual_up_vector (v').
This program does not “model transform” the cube,
but moves the camera position along a circular pass
surrounding the cube,
making it appear as if the cube is spinning.
The camera always views the origin,
which is the center of the cube, as its target.
We use the glm::lookAt function in this program.
Projection matrix is set in main().
Since the projection matrix does not change
during program execution,
you only need to set it once in main.
The model matrix is left as identity,
so there is no change in the cube.
COP, the position of the camera,
moves along an orbit parallel to the xz plane over time.
The radius of the circular orbit is 5.
The coordinates of COP given to the glm::lookAt function
are given as (camX, 1.5, camZ).
That is, the camera is slightly floating in the y direction,
parallel to the xz plane.
The camera's lens is tilted slightly downward,
looking toward the origin.
That is, at point A is given as the origin.
The virtual up vector, v', is given as the y-axis of the world,
allowing glm::lookAt to calculate the correct V vector.