In this note, we learn about projection
transformation and viewport transformation,
which convert view space to clip space.
The clipping process refers to the process of separating the inner part
from the outer part
and drawing only the inner part
when a triangle spans the boundary of the clipping volume.
In the picture on the left,
only the parts inside the clipping volume among the triangles are visible,
and the remaining parts that are clipped out are not visible on the screen.
The picture on the right lists
the cases in which line segments can be positioned
relative to the clipping volume.
A is completely outside the clipping volume, B
is completely inside, and C and D
are partially inside.
Because an object defined in 3D must be drawn on a 2D screen,
mapping from 3D to 2D is necessary.
This process is called projection.
In the picture, you can see that points are projected as points
where the projectors and the view plane intersect.
Here, the projector is the COP, that is, a straight line
connecting the position of the camera
and the point on the object.
There are two types of projection.
First, parallel projection is when the COP is infinitely far away.
All projectors are parallel.
In this case, the size ratio
of the object is maintained and projected.
It is different from the real world
we live in because
there is no sense of perspective.
Parallel projection is used in mechanical design
where accuracy in size or distance is required.
In perspective projection, the COP exists
at a finite distance.
This is a more realistic projection method.
Distant objects are projected as small and close objects are projected as large,
so the ratio of their actual size is not maintained.
In computer graphics,
perspective projection is mostly used.
Parallel projection is simple.
Just keep the x and y coordinates of the 3D coordinates
and ignore the z coordinate.
Let d be the distance between COP and view plane.
Assume that Point Pc = (xc, yc, zc) exists in camera space.
The parallel projection matrix is as simple as this.
The x and y coordinates remain the same,
and the z coordinate becomes d.
There is a parallel projection matrix provided by GLM.
The glm::ortho function is used,
and the parameters represent the left and right ranges,
bottom and top ranges,
and near and far ranges, respectively.
Only those within this range will be clipped and converted to NDC.
Now let's define the view volume to take perspective
projection into account.
View volume is also called viewing frustum.
This is a truncated pyramid,
In other words, it looks like a pyramid with its head
cut off and laid on its side.
Only objects that exist between the near and far plane
are projected onto the view plane.
Often, the view plane and near clip plane
are set to be the same.
The viewing direction that the camera faces is perpendicular to the view plane, near plane,
and far plane, and the viewing direction
vector passes through the center of each plane.
Let Pc = (xc, yc, zc)
be a point on the top plane of the view volume in view space.
Assume that by projecting Pc onto the view plane, we obtain point Ps
= (xs, ys, zs).
Here zs is equal to d, the distance from the COP to the view plane.
ys can be found by the proportional formula for similar triangles.
That is, ys/d is equal to yc/dc, so ys = d * (yc/zc).
Using a similar process,
we can also find the value of xs.
Using the xs and ys coordinates obtained previously,
let's find
the 4x4 matrix of perspective transformation.
Matrix T_pers is a matrix
that projects view coordinates onto the view plane.
The T_pers matrix looks like this.
If you look closely, you can see that the bottom row is [0, 0, 1, 0],
not [0, 0, 0, 1].
Because of this, the w-coordinate of the transformation result is not 1.
By dividing the x, y, and z components
by the w component of these homogenous coordinates,
you can finally obtain a projected result like this.
It does not stop at projection,
but also performs something called normalization transformation.
At this time, the coordinates change
from projection space to NDC.
In NDC, the 2D (xs, ys) coordinates created by projection are transformed into squares
where x and y range from -1 to 1, respectively.
In addition, rather than simply fixing the coordinates of zc
to d, the original camera
coordinates zc are scaled based on d = -1, f = 1.
When Large (X,Y) is called the (x,y)
normalized coordinates of NDC and h
is half the length of one side of the view
plane window, (X,Y) can be obtained by a proportional expression like this.
The z-coordinate in Canonical form is by squishing zc into the [-1,1] interval.
At this time, d = -1, f = 1 are the standards.
Let Large Z be the z-coordinate of canonical form.
Large Z can be found in this way.
To check, insert d and f
into zc, and large Z becomes 0 and 1, respectively.
So how can this expression be expressed
in a 4x4 matrix?
Now let's combine all processes
including normalization into perspective transformation.
Coordinates in canonical form can be expressed as homogeneous
coordinates [X, Y, Z, W].
And, the perspective transform matrix is like this.
The perspective matrix can also be easily defined using GLM.
This is done by using the glm::perspective function.
The first parameter, fov,
is an abbreviation for field of view
and indicates the angle of how wide
the view can be.
fov represents the view volume angle in the y direction
as shown in the figure.
Aspect ratio refers to the ratio of width/height.
near and far represent the distance from the camera
to the near plane and far plane.
There are many reasons why the canonical form is useful,
but the most representative
one is that clipping can be easily done
using the c anonical form, as shown here.
Let's assume a clipping test in the case
where it is not normalized.
To test whether a point is inside the view frustum,
you must perform an in/out test of the point
on the planes that form the boundary of the view frustum.
Also, in order to find only the in-part of the object that spans in/out, the intersection between the plane
and the object must also be found.
This calculation is quite complex and time consuming.
On the other hand, what about using canonical form?
The point in/out test is very simple
as it tests whether the x or y coordinate
is between -1 and 1.
Additionally, intersection calculations become much simpler.
As such, there are advantages to using the canonical form.
Viewport refers to the rectangle on the screen where the picture is drawn.
There are many cases where the entire screen becomes a viewport.
We need to convert the (x,y) coordinates of the canonical form to the pixel
coordinates of the viewport window.
As seen in the previous slide,
the (x,y) coordinates of the canonical form
are in the range of [-1,1], respectively.
This converts from Canonical form
(X,Y) to viewport coordinates (Vx, Vy) and so on.
If you substitute (-1,-1) into Large (X,Y), you get (x1, y1).
Substituting (1, 1) gives (x2, y2).
We will omit the detailed explanation of the equation.