Let’s start the ArcBall lecture
This is a program introducing ArcBall
You can rotate objects by holding down the left mouse
button and dragging
By pressing the 'a' key, you can toggle between the modes
for rotating the camera and rotating the object
The 'r' key initializes the arcball interface
and returns it to its initial state
Arcball is an interface
that is implemented as software and allows you to control rotation with just a mouse
This is a simulation of an actual trackball device
The Trackball device looks like the picture
and allows you to enter rotation data by rolling a protruding ball with your hand
Now let's place the virtual hemisphere on the computer screen
A point (x,y,z) on the hemisphere can be mapped to a point
(x,y,0) on the screen
Conversely, let's assume that you specify a point
(x,y,0) on the screen with the mouse
From this point, you can map the points
(x,y,z) on the hemisphere
The x,y values are the same as coordinates on the screen
Since the equation of the sphere is x^2+ y^2 + z^2 = 1,
the z value can be found with sqrt(1 - x^2 - y^2)
In other words, any location specified on the screen
with the mouse can be mapped to 3D point coordinates on the arcball
In that case, the corner of the screen
other than the part projected on the screen,
In other words, how can the coordinates of the part
shown in red in the picture be mapped to the hemisphere?
The mouse coordinates of this part
are changed to the nearest point
on the hemisphere for mapping
Now let's consider two points
p1 and p2 on the hemisphere mapped from two mouse coordinates on the screen
Our goal is to obtain the rotation transformation
matrix indicated by the input action
when the mouse is dragged from p1 to p2
To find such a transformation,
we need to find the rotation axis and rotation angle
The rotation axis can be easily obtained by cross
producting the two vectors heading from the origin to points
p1 and p2 on the hemisphere
The rotation angle can be obtained from the dot
product of the p1 and p2 vectors
By definition, the dot product of p1 and p2 is the product of the size of p1
and the size of p2 multiplied by cos(theta),
where theta is the angle between the two vectors p1 and p2
The two vectors p1 and p2 are on a unit sphere
with a radius of 1, and the magnitude of both vectors is 1
Therefore, theta is equal to the arccosine of the dot
product of p1 and p2
Now, using the rotation axis and angle,
you can find the rotation transformation matrix
using the “rotation
about any axis” or “quaternion” formulas you learned previously
Arcball is implemented in our code as the Arcball class,
located in arcball.h in the utils folder
First, if we look at the member variables,
they contain the width and height of the window
The mouseEvent variable indicates the state
in which the left button of the mouse is pressed
rollSpeed is multiplied by the amount of rotation the arcball produces,
and serves to control it
so that it does not make too much or too little rotation depending on the mouse movement
The angle variable stores the rotation angle calculated via the dot product
prevPos and currPos store the mouse's previous and current coordinates
as the mouse is dragged,
representing two points on the arcball hemisphere
camAxis stores the rotation axis
calculated as the cross product
Lastly, xAxis and yAxis are two boolean variables
that indicate whether mouse movement in the x or y direction
should be applied to rotation
Usually, both directions are considered,
so both are often set to true
The toScreenCoord function of the Arcball class
converts a given mouse position
(x,y) between (0,0) and (windowWidth, windowHeight) into "glm::vec3 coord",
which is normalized coordinates on the hemisphere
coord's x, y, and z all have values between [-1, 1]
In the part where mouse position coordinates
(x, y) are changed between [-1, 1],
the glm::clamp function is used to limit the mouse position
to only within the window
The z-coordinate of coord is calculated using the sphere equation
If x^2 + y^2 > 1, that is,
the mouse was in the corner of the window,
just set coord.z to 0
and normalize coord.x and coord.y
so that they are on the unit sphere.
The cursorCallback function
continues to calculate rotation transformation
when new coordinates (x, y) are input while the mouse is dragging
When the previous position on the hemisphere
obtained from mouse input is stored in prevPos,
and the position on the hemisphere
created from the new mouse position (x, y) is curPos,
the angle calculation uses the dot product as mentioned before
And the rotation axis is found using the cross product
The createRotationMatrix function creates
and returns a rotation
matrix using the axis and angle obtained through mouse movement
Now let's look at main.cpp
First, you need to include arcball.h,
which contains the arcball class
And define arcballSpeed, which can control the rotation
speed of the arcball
Because the arcball rotates very quickly,
arcballSpeed is usually defined as a value less than 1
Now create the arcballs you will use using the constructor
We defined different arcballs,
one for the rotation of the camera view
and one for the rotation of the center cube
The bool type variable arcballCamRot distinguishes whether the current rotation mode
is camera rotation mode
(true) or object rotation mode (false)
In camera rotation mode, the camera view rotates, and in object rotation mode,
the central cube rotates
In the render() function, if the camera is in rotation mode, the view matrix
obtained with glm::lookAt is further multiplied by the rotation
obtained with camArcBall.createViewRotationMatrix()
And for the center cube, the rotation matrix
obtained with modelArcBall.createRotationMatrix()
must be further multiplied by the current model transformation matrix
Except for the center cube,
the cubes on both sides do not use the arcball interface
Therefore, all you have to do
is draw a modeling transformation that moves them to the appropriate location
In keyboard callback, arcballs
are initialized when the 'r' key is entered
When the 'a' key is pressed, arcballCamRot changes to toggle
In mouse button callback and cursor position
callback, you can call the appropriate arcball class functions