Let's start the texture mapping lecture
Let's try to express realism step by step in
drawing CG scenes
In the first picture, the geometry of the objects that appear
In other words, it only uses shapes, so it is not very realistic
The next one uses Phong shading,
but it's still missing something
The last one uses shading and texture maps together,
and looks much more realistic
Texture mapping adds
realistic details to CG scenes
Rendering is done by wrapping an object in a detailed 2D image
If all of these details were to be implemented through modeling alone,
a large number of vertices and faces would be needed,
making it very difficult and complicated
Texture mapping provides a much more efficient method
Texture mapping was published as part of the doctoral thesis of Edwin Catmull,
who graduated from the University of Utah in 1974
He is a co-founder of the famous animation production company Pixar
and serves as CEO of Walt Disney Animation Studio
He won the ACM Turing Award in 2019
In addition to texture-mapping, he is a pioneer
who invented many important technologies
essential to current CG,
such as bicubic surface,
spatial anti-aliasing, subdivision surface, and z-buffering
Texture mapping technology was further developed by Catmull's successors,
Blinn and Newell
Let me first explain the term texture coordinates
These coordinates are used to specify the position
on the texture image
Typically denoted as (u,v) or (s,t)
Also, both the horizontal and vertical axes
have values between 0 and 1
Let’s take a look at the role texture coordinates play
Here is a texture image in the shape of an electronic circuit board
This texture image has texture coordinates specified
Let's assume that we have a simple mesh
that will be the source of texture mapping
The shape of this mesh is not rectangular but slightly distorted
Now, let's give texture coordinates to the four vertices
so that the texture image is mapped to the mesh
First, in the first method, texture coordinates (0,0),
(1,0), (1,1), (0,1) were given to the four vertices
In this way, the entire area of the texture image is mapped to the mesh
Because the mesh is distorted, the image is also distorted
and looks a little different from the original texture
In the second method, I changed the texture
coordinates to use only part of the texture image
That is, instead of (1,0) and (1,1), we gave (0.9, 0.4) and (1, 0.7)
Although the entire texture image has not been mapped,
you can see that distortion is prevented
Texture coordinates can be used to specify which
part of the texture image should be mapped to
an object like this
Texture coordinates typically range from (0,0)
to (1,1)
What happens if texture coordinates exceed this range?
OpenGL's default handles these cases with the GL_REPEAT option
In other words, the same texture image is repeated over and over again
This is the case on the far left of the picture
GL_MIRROERED_REPEAT repeats, but changes
direction at the boundary line
so that it is reflected in a mirror
GL_CLAMP_TO_EDGE continues to repeat only the pixels
at the border of the texture image
GL_CLAMP_TO_BORDER repeats the specific color
set as the border color
The rightmost part of the picture
shows a case where a dark green border color is used
In many cases, the two axis directions of texture coordinates
are denoted as s and t
s represents the horizontal axis and t represents the vertical axis
The method of wrapping the texture is specified
using GL_TEXTURE_WRAP_S or GL_TEXTURE_WRAP_T
of the glTexParameteri function
In this example, both the S and T directions are set to GL_MIRROERED_REPEAT
You can also specify the border
color of the texture using glTexParameterfv
The i attached to the end of glTexParameter
indicates integer and fv indicates float vector type
The difference in size and number of texture
map images and screen pixels fundamentally causes aliasing problems in texture mapping
In this picture, the checkered texture map image
is mapped to a perspective projected trapezoid
Points corresponding to texture and polygon
are indicated in the picture
The trapezoid is rasterized and the texture colors corresponding to each pixel are extracted and mapped
as shown on the far right
However, it is clear that this is not a good outcome
To prevent this, anti-aliasing techniques should be used
This picture shows a case where aliasing occurs
and the texture is broken on the left,
and the texture mapping result is improved
using anti-aliasing on the right
Simply, there is a filtering method that determines the color
by averaging the surrounding texel colors
There is also an oversampling method that splits the
texture's texels into smaller pieces
Let’s learn more about filtering methods
There are cases where the texture needs to be enlarged or reduced
because the sizes of the pixels representing the texture
and polygon do not match exactly
For example, when one pixel
P of a polygon is mapped to a quadrilateral
made up of multiple texels in the texture,
the texture image must be minified
Conversely, if multiple pixels of a polygon
are mapped to only one texel of a texture,
the texture image must be magnified
In most cases, the pixel of the polygon
on which the texture will be applied
does not exactly match the texel of the texture image
In this case, the process of calculating the color to be painted on the polygon
pixel from the texture image is called "texture
filtering." "Nearest filter" is OpenGL's default filtering method
When using nearest filtering, if a red polygon pixel spans multiple texture
texels as shown in the picture,
the texel color of the texture to which the center of the pixel belongs is used
There is no additional processing
such as combining the surrounding colors and averaging them
This method helps reduce texture mapping time,
but the quality of texture
mapping across the entire polygon is likely to be not very good
This is because the colors of neighboring polygon pixels may change rapidly
Since it is the default method,
there is no need to specify the filtering method separately,
but you can specify the GL_TEXTURE_MIN_FILTER
or GL_TEXTURE_MAG_FILTER value of glTexParameteri
as GL_NEAREST like this
The method introduced this time is a method of interpolation
by averaging the texel colors around the texel
containing the specified texture
coordinates (center of the polygon pixel), and is called a “linear
filter” or “bilinear filter.”
In the picture, a red polygon pixel spans multiple texels,
and the color that is determined
is the interpolated color that is appropriately averaged
To explain this method simply, the closer
the distance from the polygon pixel center to the texel center
being considered, the more the proportion of the color
of that texel is increased
To perform texture filtering using this method,
GL_TEXTURE_MIN_FILTER or GL_TEXTURE_MAG_FILTER must be specified
in the GL_LINEAR method
We compared the texture mapping results when using the nearest filter
and linear filter, respectively
In the case of the nearest filter on the left,
the color change of the texture texel
mapped to each screen pixel became severe,
so the results were so bad
that the boundaries of neighboring pixels could not be recognized
However, each pixel color appears very clearly
In the case of the linear filter on the right,
the color of the pixel is determined
by interpolating the colors of neighboring texels,
so you can see that
the color of neighboring pixels changes flexibly
However, overall, the results after texture
mapping show that the boundaries of objects appearing in the image are not clear
It can be seen as a trade-off between the two methods
Mipmap refers to preparing texture
images of different sizes in advance before rendering
OpenGL has a command that allows the user to load one texture image
and then create and prepare a mipmap
This way, you can select and use an appropriate texture image
according to the size of the texture image that occupies the screen pixel
In other words, keep the screen pixel size and texture
texel size as similar as possible
Whether or not the Mipmap method is used
has a significant impact on the quality of the final texture mapping
In the picture, the left side represents the case where mipmap is not applied,
and the right side represents the case where mipmap is applied
This is another comparison
result with and without mipmap applied
The picture on the left is without a mipmap,
and the picture on the right is with a mipmap
If there is no mipmap, the difference in texture color
mapped between screen pixel neighbors may become severe,
causing severe flickering
OpenGL has a function that creates a mipmap chain
of the loaded texture image
The function used there is “glGenerateMipmaps”
GL_TEXTURE_2D can usually be used
as a parameter target
The mipmap chain continues
until only one pixel remains at the final level
As the level increases, the resolution decreases
by 1/2 of the width and height,
and the size of the image, that is,
the width and height, also decreases by 1/2 of the lower level
After a mipmap is created, you can use the option with the mipmap function
added as a filtering method
First, the NEAREST in front of GL_NEAREST_MIPMAP_NEAREST
indicates how to simply take the color
of the nearest texel, as mentioned before
NEAREST at the end
indicates which of several mipmaps to use
Since it is NEAREST, the image with the texel size
most similar to the current pixel size
is selected from the mipmap hierarchy
GL_LINEAR_MIPMAP_NEAREST uses the LINEAR interpolation method
when determining color, and simply selects nearest mipmap
GL_NEAREST_MIPMAP_LINEAR determines the color using the NEAREST method,
but creates and uses a texture image of a new size
by linearly interpolating between two mipmap images
with texels of the size
most similar to the size of the screen pixel
GL_LINEAR_MIPMAP_LINEAR calculates color determination using a linear method and mipmap image determination
using a linear interpolation method
Therefore, it takes the most calculation time
Let's take an example of texture mapping using Mipmap
Base texture has a resolution of 8x4
OpenGL generates a mipmap
by averaging 2x2 texels from the base texture
and reducing the image
For example, texel '3' of the lower 4x2 mipmap was obtained by averaging the 2x2 texels (4,
2, 3, 3) of the upper base texture
Now assume that one pixel of the rasterized triangle is mapped to 2x2
texels of the base texture
In other words, this is a case
where minification must be applied to texels
In this case, rather than mapping
the 2x2 texels of the base texture,
we can fetch and use texel '3' of the pre-created 4x2 mipmap
This can reduce computation time in the middle of rendering
and, depending on how you create
the mipmap, can also improve rendering quality
This is the first example program where texture mapping is applied
The same texture is mapped to all six sides of the cube
Now let's take a look again at the texture
coordinates part of the Cube class defined in cube.h
Cube has 8 vertexes from index 0 to 7
as shown in the picture above
Among these, considering the rectangle (v0, v1, v2, v3), which is the front
face, the texture coordinates (1,0), (0, 0), (0, 1), (1,1)
are v0, v1, v2, respectively. , mapped to v3
Just look at the yellow arrows in the picture
In other words, the left and right and top and bottom of the texture image are reversed and mapped
This is not a common case, and in fact,
in this example, the texture map image is symmetrical left and right and top and bottom,
so there is no major problem
However, in the general case, it is correct
that (1, 1), (0,1), (0, 0), and (1,0)
are mapped to v0, v1, v2, and v3, respectively
When filling data into the VBO in the buffer initialization
part of cube.h, the size of the total sum of position,
normal, color, and texture coordinates
data is first set as glBufferData
Then, I used glBufferSubData
to give an offset of vSize+nSize+cSize
and copy
the texture coordinates data to the buffer
At the very end of the cube's buffer initialization,
in the part where data is transmitted to the vertex shader,
the texture coordinates data is transmitted to the
shader's attribute variable number 3
The data type is an array of 2D vectors
Texture coordinates that have been ignored in the vertex shader
must now be used
Texture coordinates, a 2D vector,
were transferred from the application program
to the variable "aTexCoord" at location number 3
These texture coordinates are passed to the fragment shader,
using the out variable toTexCoord
In the fragment shader, the texture coordinates passed from the vertex shader
are received as the in variable "toTexCoord"
Please note that the type and name of toTexCoord are the same as the out
variable in the vertex shader
The type of shader variable for texture map is sampler2D
"Texture" is a predefined shader
function that calculates the color of the texel
given as texture coordinates from the texture map,
and this color is assigned as the final color, FragColor
The application program uses the above
two lines to include the stb_image.h library function
stbi_image can read image files in various formats,
such as bmp, jpg, and png, as textures
In the loadTexture() function, all preparations for texture mapping are made
and the texture image is loaded
First, generate a texture object and receive its ID
As with VAO and VBO, multiple texture
objects can be generated simultaneously
glBindTexture is a command to use this texture object
in all subsequent
texture-related operations or rendering
In specifying the method to be used in texture
wrapping, GL_CLAMP is used in the s direction and GL_REPEAT
is used in the t direction
In fact, in this program, wrapping is not used
because the texture coordinates never deviate from the [0,1] range in both
the horizontal and vertical directions
In this part, filtering methods for texture
minification and maginification
are specified,
and all are specified in the GL_LINEAR method
The next part of loadTexture reads the image file into stbi_load,
a library function of stb_image
It also handles errors that may occur while reading the file
The glTexImage2D function copies
image data to the currently bound texture object
The glGenerateMipmap function generates
a mipmap of a texture object