This is a Texture Examples lecture
In the Texture2 program, the texture image is displayed
mapped to one square
Each time you press the space bar,
the texture mode changes to 1, 2, 3, 0, 1, 2, 3,
0, … It changes repeatedly as follows
Different texture mapping is applied each time
This part shows three arrays containing vertex coordinates,
vertex color, and texture
coordinates data for rectangle data used in the program
The genRectangle function fills the VBO
with three attributes: vertex position,
color, and texture coordinates
Similar to cube,
each data was copied to VBO
using glBufferData and glBufferSubData
Before drawing an object using a texture, bind
the desired texture
When texCoordState is mode 0,
the four vertices of the square have normal texture
coordinates of 0 and 1
Texture mapping is done so that the entire image fits
perfectly into a square
We called the genRectangle() function again
to change the texture
coordinates and overwrite them in the VBO
However, since only the texture coordinates have changed,
there is no need to run genRectangle() in its entirety
Just rewrite the part that uses texture
coordinates as glBufferSubData
In mode 1, the texture coordinates of the rectangular vertices were specified
as shown in the picture
Only 1/4 of the texture image
is mapped and drawn in the rectangle
In mode 2, the texture
coordinates of the rectangular vertices were designated as (-1,0),
(2,0), (2,1), (-1,1) as shown in the picture
The y-direction is normal between [0,1],
but the x-direction has no fixed texture in the [-1,0]
and [1,2] parts, so wrapping must be used
The image is reduced by 1/3 in width and placed in the center
This is because the texture image must be mapped to the area
where texture coordinates are [0,1]
The remaining left and bottom parts
repeat the original image
because the wrapping option
in the s direction is set to GL_REPEAT
In mode 3, the range of texture coordinates
in both horizontal and vertical directions
is given between [-1,2]
Therefore, normal teture mapping is performed only on the horizontal
and vertical [0,1] x [0,1] portion,
and all remaining portions are determined by the wrapping option
As confirmed on the previous page,
both wrapping options in the s and t directions are GL_REPEAT,
so the result is as shown in the picture
The MultiTexture program is a program that maps
two texture maps to the same location at the same time
We created texture1 and texture2 objects
by loading two texture images
“container.bmp” and “awesomeface.bmp” respectively
After loading the two textures,
they were referred to as 0 and 1
respectively and passed through the fragment shader
This number is called a “texture unit”
The names of the uniform
variables that receive each texture
within the fragment shader
are texture1 and texture2, respectively
Texture units passed by the application program
are received as uniform
sampler2D variables within the fragment shader
Using the utility function
"mix", the colors of texture1
and texture2 are mixed at a ratio of 0.8:0.2
and the final color, FragColor, is calculated
Before drawing, the texture to be used must be bound
In this example, two textures must be used,
so both must be bided
So, first activate one texture unit
with glActiveTexture(),
bind that texture, and then proceed
to the next one
The constants used in glActiveTexture,
GL_TEXTURE0, GL_TEXTURE1,
..., can be considered to represent texture units 0, 1, 2, ...
in that order, respectively
The OpenGL specification
requires support of at least 16 texture units
Texture unit constants have continuous values,
so they can be specified through
simple operations
For example, GL_TEXTURE8 is equivalent to (GL_TEXTURE0
+ 8)
Using this property, it becomes possible to bind textures
using a loop
The ColorTexture program is a program
that renders by simultaneously utilizing vertex
color and texture mapping
In this program, we tell the fragment shader
to calculate the final color
by multiplying the given vertex color by the texture color
Since all color values are in the [0,1] range,
the value multiplied by them also exists in the [0, 1] range